<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ray Peat Explained</title>
    <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ray Peat Explained</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raypeatexplained.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on acetazolamide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-acetazolamide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-acetazolamide/</guid>
      <description>Treating New Diseases with High Altitude Edema Medication &#34;using calcium channel blockers and acetazolamide to treat the new disease, because of their therapeutic effect in high altitude pulmonary edema. He didn’t mention it, but both of these drugs can correct the tissue deficiency of carbon dioxide.&#34;
- May 2020 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Treatments for Altitude Sickness and CO2 Retention &#34;Like acetazolamide, the other recognized treatment for altitude sickness, calcium channel blockers inhibit carbonic anhydrase, facilitating the body’s retention of CO2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on adaptation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</guid>
      <description>The Costly Adaptations of Serotonin Production &#34;Stresses of different sorts increase the formation of serotonin and the various pituitary hormones, leading to adaptive changes in the organism, but at the cost of causing inflammation and degeneration. Studies of several of the pituitary hormones have shown age-accelerating effects, leading to edema, inflammation, fibrosis, and decreased longevity. W.D. Denckla’s experiments showing the great life extending effect of removing the pituitary gland, while supplementing thyroid and glucocorticoid hormones, suggest the possibilities inherent in finding ways to prevent the over-production of serotonin and its associated hormones and cytokines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on adrenalin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adrenalin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adrenalin/</guid>
      <description>Adrenal Response to Inflammation and Stress Hormones &#34;When the organism detects the inflammation or other stress (possibly by sensing changes in blood sugar, lactic acid, or carbon dioxide, or all of them) its adrenal glands will secrete anti-stress hormones, including adrenalin and cortisone (assuming these glands are not exhausted or starved). Both adrenalin and cortisone can raise blood sugar to meet the increased need.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Blood Sugar as an Integrating Factor for Stress &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aging</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aging/</guid>
      <description>Young vs. Aging Brain Cholesterol &#34;The healthy young brain contains a very large amount of cholesterol, almost all in the pure, non-esterified or free form—more than 99.5%, according to Orth and Bellosta (2012, citing Bjorkhem and Meaney, 2004). The aging, degenerating brain contains an increasing amount of esterified cholesterol,&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nighttime Parathyroid Hormone Activity and Calcium Loss &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ammonia</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ammonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ammonia/</guid>
      <description>Digestive Processing of Seeds and Associated Allergic Reactions &#34;If we eat seeds in the crude form, our digestive enzymes handle the glutin differently, producing some fairly toxic peptides (chemically related to histamine) and some ammonia; these, added to the starch, can cause gas and a variety of allergic reactions&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Carbon Dioxide, Urea, and Water Regulation &#34;Besides this fundamental stabilizing, regulatory function of carbon dioxide, it combines with ammonia to form urea.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on antioxidants</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-antioxidants/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-antioxidants/</guid>
      <description>Lifestyle Choices to Slow Aging and Enhance Longevity &#34;Altitude and a milk based diet are obviously two important thermogenic factors that slow the accumulation of harmful adaptations, but there are many other controllable factors that could extend longevity even more. Reducing inflammatory factors is important, and personal choices can make a big difference, for example choosing easily digestible foods to reduce endotoxin, avoiding the polyunsaturated fatty acids that interfere with cell respiration and form inflammatory prostaglandins, avoiding antioxidant supplements that create a reductive excess, and choosing foods that contain antiinflammatory-thermogenic compounds, such as citrus fruits with their high content of flavonoids that support cell respiratory functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aspirin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</guid>
      <description>Nutritional Adjustments Required for Various Drugs Including Estrogen &#34;Any drug alters your nutritional needs. Tobacco, iron, aspirin, estrogen, tranquilizers and diuretics must be taken into account. There are special diets for special needs.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Standard Atrial Fibrillation Treatment Versus Thermogenic Agents &#34;The standard treatment for atrial fibrillation is destruction of part of the conduction system of the heart, called ablation, which costs more than $25,000 in the U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ATP</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</guid>
      <description>Biological Water Retention and Cell Energy Relations &#34;The retention of water by the living substance is a topic that reductionist biology has been reluctant to discuss. There are no pumps for biological water, and it took a long time for a water channel protein to be proposed. The structural molecules of a cell, its metabolites and water are mutually dissolved, and their affinity for each other is affected by the cell’s energetic relation to its environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on biological energy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</guid>
      <description>Hypothyroidism Effects on Muscle Fatigue and Metabolites &#34;When metabolic energy is failing, as in hypothyroidism, muscles become easily fatigued, and take up excess water, and the barrier structure is loosened, allowing macromolecules and ATP and other metabolites to leak out, while extraneous substances enter. Typical muscle enzymes such as lactate dehydrogenase and creatine kinase appear in the bloodstream in typical hypothyroid myopathy, and heart proteins, including a particular form of lactic dehydrogenase and a muscle protein, troponin, appear in the blood after a heart stress or fatigue combined with hypothyroidism or systemic inflammation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on biotin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biotin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biotin/</guid>
      <description>Importance of Biotin in Nervous System Fat Synthesis &#34;Biotin is involved in the synthesis of fats in the nervous system, and so should probably be given special attention in the MS diet.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Treating Lactic Acid Excess with Glycolysis Inhibition &#34;Heart failure, shock, and other problems involving excess lactic acid can be treated successfully by poisoning glycolysis with dichloroacetic acid, reducing the production of lactic acid, increasing the oxidation of glucose, and increasing cellular ATP concentration: Thyroid, vitamin B1, biotin, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on breast cancer</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-breast-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-breast-cancer/</guid>
      <description>Psychoactive Substances and Their Effects on Chronic Conditions &#34;During LSD research, it was noticed that people with chronic headaches, asthma, or psoriasis sometimes recovered completely during treatment with frequent doses of LSD. Another alkaloid derived from ergot, bromocriptine, is now being used to suppress lactation (such as is caused by prolactin-secreting pituitary tumor which develops after using oral contraceptives) and is used experimentally to treat Parkinsons disease. Both LSD and bromocriptine shift the ratio of two brain chemicals, DOPA and serotonin, towards DOPA dominance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on calcium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-calcium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-calcium/</guid>
      <description>Parathyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role and Effects in Aging &#34;Phosphate, which predominates in grains, beans, nuts, meats, and fish, increases our production of parathyroid hormone, while calcium and magnesium inhibit its production. This hormone, which increases with age, suppresses immunity, and in excess it causes insomnia, seizures, dementia, psychosis, cancer, heart disease, respiratory distress and pulmonary hypertension, osteoporosis, sarcopenia, histamine release, inflammation and soft tissue calcification, and many other problems.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cancer</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cancer/</guid>
      <description>Inflammation&amp;#39;s Role in Chronic Diseases &#34;inflammation is seen to be intrinsic to the disease process itself, in an increasing number of the chronic and degenerative diseases—dementia, psychosis, atherosclerosis, osteoporosis, cancer, for example.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Aerobic Glycolysis and Lactic Acid in Cancer Metabolism &#34;Aerobic glycolysis, the metabolism characteristic of cancer, in which lactic acid is produced from glucose despite the presence of oxygen, is promoted by serotonin&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on carbon monoxide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-carbon-monoxide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-carbon-monoxide/</guid>
      <description>Questioning Neodarwinism Through Hormetic Toxin Analysis &#34;If toxins such as CO and NO are beneficial, hormetically, when they occur in city air, then obviously they must be very beneficial when they are produced in the body by enzymes, which evolved through the natural selection of things that supported survival—there is a clear Panglossian aspect to neodarwinism, everything exists because of its fitness.&#34;
- November 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cholesterol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cholesterol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cholesterol/</guid>
      <description>Hypothyroidism&amp;#39;s Link to Atherosclerosis &#34;Several people in the 1930s and *40s showed that hypothyroidism caused atherosclerosis, and that thyroid supplementation corrected it. In people whose thyroid gland was removed, their serum cholesterol increased as their rate of metabolism slowed, and when they were given desiccated thyroid to normalize their metabolic rate, their serum cholesterol was immediately correspondingly normalized.&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Role in Progesterone Production &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ciproheptadine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</guid>
      <description>Factors for Healthier Pregnancies and Postpartum Life &#34;the most important factors that can be optimized with existing resources. Healthier pregnancies will result in healthier and happier postpartum life. Some of these factors would be sunlight, vitamin D, milk, cheese, eggs, fruits and well cooked vegetables, fibrous foods, and optimizing thyroid function and pregnenolone and progesterone (which support mitochondrial function, protecting against aldosterone, parathyroid hormone, excess serotonin, CRK, and cortisol, besides increasing allopregnanolone), and using the safest antiinflammatory and antiserotonin drugs, such as aspirin and cyproheptadine, when they are needed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on CO2</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-co2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-co2/</guid>
      <description>Hyperventilation, CO2 Loss, and Serotonin Release &#34;Hyperventilation tends to increase under various stresses, and the resulting loss of carbon dioxide increases the alkalinity of the blood, which causes the platelets to release serotonin. Estrogenic stimulation and hypothyroidism are common causes of chronic hyperventilation, with its effect on platelets, releasing serotonin, with all its harmful consequences.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Tissue Response to Stimulation and Oxygen Utilization &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on coconut oil</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-coconut-oil/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-coconut-oil/</guid>
      <description>Weight Loss Through Increased Caloric Intake with Coconut Oil &#34;I noticed that I was losing weight, while eating more calories than normal, because of adding about an ounce of coconut oil to my usual diet. After several months, I leveled off at a weight about 15 pounds lower than my normal weight of the previous 26 years.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Benefits of Coconut Oil on Thyroid and Health &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on coffee</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-coffee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-coffee/</guid>
      <description>Defective Mental Energy Storage and Stimulant Effects &#34;The individual with a defective mental energy storage system might dash around keeping his mind stimulated, or it might be that coffee or other nerve stimulants will raise the level of energy to the point that quiet integration becomes possible.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Dark Roast Coffee Providing Minimum Daily Vitamin B1 &#34;In a study of the thiamine content of dark roast coffee, it was found that one or two cups provide the minimum daily requirement of vitamin B1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on copper</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</guid>
      <description>Copper&amp;#39;s Synergistic Effects with Estrogen &#34;Copper seems to be synergic with estrogen, and could have a similar effect&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nutritional and Hormonal Impacts on Cellular Respiration &#34;Various nutritional, hormonal, or toxic states interfere with respiration in different ways: for example, vitamin E deficiency, estrogen excess, toxic thyroid, and DNP (the formerly popular cancer-causing reducing drug) cause oxygen to be consumed without producing the normal amount of useful energy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cortisol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</guid>
      <description>The Costly Adaptations of Serotonin Production &#34;Stresses of different sorts increase the formation of serotonin and the various pituitary hormones, leading to adaptive changes in the organism, but at the cost of causing inflammation and degeneration. Studies of several of the pituitary hormones have shown age-accelerating effects, leading to edema, inflammation, fibrosis, and decreased longevity. W.D. Denckla’s experiments showing the great life extending effect of removing the pituitary gland, while supplementing thyroid and glucocorticoid hormones, suggest the possibilities inherent in finding ways to prevent the over-production of serotonin and its associated hormones and cytokines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on depression</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-depression/</guid>
      <description>BBB and Cellular Stress: Evidence in Blood &#34;The Blood Brain Barrier, BBB, has sometimes been treated as something unique, but it’s just a special case of the cellular resistance that exists everywhere. For example, after intense exercise that produces fatigue and damage to muscles, a unique brain protein, S100B, that is considered a crucial part of the BBB, can be found in the blood stream. The exchange of substances, even proteins and nucleic acids, between cells and their environment, increases during stress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on development</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-development/</guid>
      <description>Nutrient-Rich Foods&amp;#39; Role in Normal Development and Stress &#34;Any food that provides simple nutrients, without causing inflammation and blocking enzymes, will support the animal’s normal development, without activating stress responses.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Organism Development in a Stress-Free Environment &#34;When the organism is free from threats and stresses, with a permissive milieu interieur, and is able to just be itself, what does it do?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dhea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</guid>
      <description>Aging Skin, Progesterone, and Vitamin D &#34;It has been known for several decades that the production of progesterone and DHEA decreases steadily with aging, and in recent years it has been noticed that when aged skin is exposed to sunlight it produces only half as much vitamin D as young skin does. Old skin has about half as much cholesterol as young skin, so it isn’t surprising that those substances derived from it are reduced.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on digestion</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</guid>
      <description>Serotonin&amp;#39;s Production and Body Defense Mechanisms &#34;The great majority of the body’s serotonin is produced in the intestine, where the tissue is constantly exposed to foreign material such as endotoxin, but all cells in the body can produce serotonin and histamine during stress, and the blood platelets are one of the body’s defenses against serotonin; they can sequester it and carry it to the lungs for destruction. The lungs have a great capacity to oxidize it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dopamine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</guid>
      <description>Substances Opposing Estrogen in Cancer Therapy &#34;Anything which produces tissue atrophy will tend to produce cancer. The important question is, what will induce differentiation and useful function in cancer cells? There are many substances which promote differentiation and oppose the effects of estrogen, and some of these have been found to be useful in cancer therapy. Among the substances opposing estrogen are dopamine and nickel, prolactin inhibitors; chalones, the tissue specific proteins which inhibit cell division (and possibly more ephemerally, the peptides of memory); the aprotic solvents, DMF and possibly DMSO; progesterone and testosterone; thyroxin and iodine; magnesium ATP, the stable form of the biological energy molecule; vitamin A, a protein-sparing nutrient which promotes differentiation, and vitamin E (and the closely related coenzyme Q, or ubiquinone).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-epilepsy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-epilepsy/</guid>
      <description>Benefits of Coconut Oil on Thyroid and Health &#34;The easily oxidized short and medium-chain saturated fatty acids of coconut oil provide a source of energy that protects our tissues against the toxic inhibitory effects of the unsaturated fatty acids, and reduces their anti-thyroid effects. The animal studies of the last 60 years suggest that these effects also provide protection against cancer, heart disease, and premature aging. Other effects that can be expected inclu de protection against excessive blood clotting, protection of the fetal brain, protection against various stress-induced problems including epilepsy, and some degree of protection against sun-damage of the skin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on estrogen</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Effect on Tryptophan Metabolism &#34;Estrogen strongly affects the metabolism of tryptophan, increasing its conversion to serotonin at the expense of niacinamide, which accounts for the symptoms of pellagra when the diet lacks tryptophan. When there’s enough protein in the diet, promotion of serotonin synthesis won’t result in a niacinamide deficiency, but conditions that increase the influence of estrogen will also increase the malfunctions involving serotonin.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Estrogen, Serotonin, and Water Retention Cycle &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on folic acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-folic-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-folic-acid/</guid>
      <description>Nutritional Needs for Regulating Estrogen and Thyroid Function &#34;Besides the nutrients needed to regulate the estrogen level (protein and B vitamins) and nutrients needed by the thyroid (e.g., iodine, manganese, and cobalt), special attention should be given to the anti-stress vitamins which are involved in progesterone synthesis (vitamin A, pantothenic acid, vitamin C, vitamin E) and to the nutrients that are known to be wasted by excess estrogen: folic acid, zinc, and vitamin B6, particularly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on free fatty acids</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-free-fatty-acids/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-free-fatty-acids/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on fruit</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-fruit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-fruit/</guid>
      <description>Understanding and Meeting Your Body&amp;#39;s Nutritional Needs &#34;You have to learn to know what your body needs at a particular time. This will be made easier if your basic diet is roughly like that described above moderately low calorie intake, fairly high protein intake, with high quality proteins such as eggs, milk, and leaves, and with fresh fruit or vegetables every day.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Eating Patterns Combining Protein, Fat, and Carbohydrates &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on gaba</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</guid>
      <description>Biological Effects of Magnetic Fields: Sedation and Brain Chemistry Changes &#34;Magnetic fields presumably act biologically by acting on the structure of water, and Kholodov has established that a continuous sinusoidal magnetic field has a sedative and inhibiting effect, modifying the EEG and raising the level of GABA in the brain (Speranskiy, 1973). The activity of oxygen increases in magnetically treated water (Speranskiy, 1973), so there might be a direct effect on energy production.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Gilbert Ling</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</guid>
      <description>Paradox of Lipid Bilayer Membrane Doctrine &#34;The fact that cholesterol strengthens cells, keeping them from disintegrating under stress, obviously has nothing to do with a lipid bilayer membrane. That membrane doctrine has made it seem paradoxical that the loss of cholesterol should make cells stiffer, while weakening them. Gilbert Ling has, for 65 years, pointed out the numerous paradoxes confronted by the advocates of the lipid boundary membrane, but the membrane doctrine continues to govern&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on growth hormone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-growth-hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-growth-hormone/</guid>
      <description>Critical Views on Long-Term Estrogen Therapy &#34;onstance Martin, in her Textbook of Endocrine Physiology, (1976), says that estrogens are not useful if administered over long periods of time.... M.R. Urist (in Biochem. and Physiol. of Bone, vol.2, G.H. Bourne, 1972 ed.) says that estrogen doesnt restore bone mass to a degree demonstrable by roentgenography, that excessive growth hormone may aggravate the disorder, and that estrogen stimulates the release of growth hormone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Hans Selye</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</guid>
      <description>Selye&amp;#39;s Discovery of Adaptive System Phases and Stress Immunization &#34;Hans Selye found that the adrenals are a major component of our adaptive system. In the first phase of stress, there is a shock reaction (with changes resembling those of estrogen dominance), with injury to various tissues. In the second phase, the adrenals protect the animal, and this protection continues until something is exhausted. By exposing rats to a preliminary stress, Selye found that he could induce adaptation to other, later stresses — a kind of immunization to stress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on high altitude</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-high-altitude/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-high-altitude/</guid>
      <description>High Metabolic Rate&amp;#39;s Association with Longevity at Altitude &#34;In one study (Alhazmi, et al., 2018), T3 was four and a half times higher in people living at a high altitude, T4 was about three times higher, and TSH (a promoter of inflammation) was reduced by more than 25%. The high altitude studies show very convincingly that a high metabolic rate is strongly associated with greater longevity and better health.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on histamine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-histamine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-histamine/</guid>
      <description>Serotonin&amp;#39;s Production and Body Defense Mechanisms &#34;The great majority of the body’s serotonin is produced in the intestine, where the tissue is constantly exposed to foreign material such as endotoxin, but all cells in the body can produce serotonin and histamine during stress, and the blood platelets are one of the body’s defenses against serotonin; they can sequester it and carry it to the lungs for destruction. The lungs have a great capacity to oxidize it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on hyperventilation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hyperventilation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hyperventilation/</guid>
      <description>Hyperventilation, CO2 Loss, and Serotonin Release &#34;Hyperventilation tends to increase under various stresses, and the resulting loss of carbon dioxide increases the alkalinity of the blood, which causes the platelets to release serotonin. Estrogenic stimulation and hypothyroidism are common causes of chronic hyperventilation, with its effect on platelets, releasing serotonin, with all its harmful consequences.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Hypothyroidism&amp;#39;s Link to Chronic Stress and Metabolic Issues &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on inflammation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</guid>
      <description>Inflammation&amp;#39;s Role in Chronic Diseases &#34;inflammation is seen to be intrinsic to the disease process itself, in an increasing number of the chronic and degenerative diseases—dementia, psychosis, atherosclerosis, osteoporosis, cancer, for example.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Hypothyroidism Effects on Muscle Fatigue and Metabolites &#34;When metabolic energy is failing, as in hypothyroidism, muscles become easily fatigued, and take up excess water, and the barrier structure is loosened, allowing macromolecules and ATP and other metabolites to leak out, while extraneous substances enter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on insomnia</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-insomnia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-insomnia/</guid>
      <description>Parathyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role and Effects in Aging &#34;Phosphate, which predominates in grains, beans, nuts, meats, and fish, increases our production of parathyroid hormone, while calcium and magnesium inhibit its production. This hormone, which increases with age, suppresses immunity, and in excess it causes insomnia, seizures, dementia, psychosis, cancer, heart disease, respiratory distress and pulmonary hypertension, osteoporosis, sarcopenia, histamine release, inflammation and soft tissue calcification, and many other problems.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on insulin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-insulin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-insulin/</guid>
      <description>Parathyroid Hormone Reduction Linked to Obesity and Related Issues &#34;The reduction of parathyroid hormone by increased calcium and vitamin D is closely related to reduced obesity, and to the health problems associated with obesity—hypertension, insulin resistance, heart arrhythmias, depression, and various inflammatory conditions.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Pantothenic Acid&amp;#39;s Role in Hyperinsulinism Treatment &#34;Pantothenic acid is needed by the liver to destroy insulin (insulinase), so hyperinsulinism, causing hypoglycemia, can sometimes be remedied with this nutrient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on intelligence</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-intelligence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-intelligence/</guid>
      <description>Stress Hormones, Nutrition, and Longevity &#34;The hormones of stress age various tissues, including the brain, and the collagen in connective tissue. Good nutrition, including the anti-stress substances found in certain foods, will simultaneously optimize intelligence and increase the healthy life-span.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Language&amp;#39;s Influence on Devaluing Animal Intelligence &#34;If we believe that language and logic are the source of knowledge, we will devalue our own animal intelligence, and in doing this we become susceptable to the clichés and doctrines that have been deliberately built into our culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on iron</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-iron/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-iron/</guid>
      <description>Lipofuscin&amp;#39;s Role in Plaque Inflammation and Calcification &#34;The age pigment, ceroid or lipofuscin, that’s derived largely from PUFA and associated with the macrophage foam cells in the plaque, accumulates iron (Lee, et al, 1998), and by catalyzing oxidation, creates local hypoxia, leading to lactic acid production, contributing to an inflammatory process. The products of lipid peroxidation, such as azelaic acid (Riad, et al., 2018), along with lactate, lead to the calcification of tissue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on lactic acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</guid>
      <description>Hypothyroidism Effects on Muscle Fatigue and Metabolites &#34;When metabolic energy is failing, as in hypothyroidism, muscles become easily fatigued, and take up excess water, and the barrier structure is loosened, allowing macromolecules and ATP and other metabolites to leak out, while extraneous substances enter. Typical muscle enzymes such as lactate dehydrogenase and creatine kinase appear in the bloodstream in typical hypothyroid myopathy, and heart proteins, including a particular form of lactic dehydrogenase and a muscle protein, troponin, appear in the blood after a heart stress or fatigue combined with hypothyroidism or systemic inflammation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on learned helplessness</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-learned-helplessness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-learned-helplessness/</guid>
      <description>Learned Helplessness in Rats and Energy Use Efficiency &#34;About 1957, psychologists noticed that a rat could learn helplessness: if they held a rat until it stopped struggling, it would then die much sooner than a normal rat does when put into a barrel of water. They also found that they could immunize their rats against learned helplessness, by previously allowing them to experience success in a similar situation. The short-term learned helplessness apparently does something to block the efficient use of energy, so that the animal dies of exhaustion very easily, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on lipofuscin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lipofuscin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lipofuscin/</guid>
      <description>Lipofuscin&amp;#39;s Role in Plaque Inflammation and Calcification &#34;The age pigment, ceroid or lipofuscin, that’s derived largely from PUFA and associated with the macrophage foam cells in the plaque, accumulates iron (Lee, et al, 1998), and by catalyzing oxidation, creates local hypoxia, leading to lactic acid production, contributing to an inflammatory process. The products of lipid peroxidation, such as azelaic acid (Riad, et al., 2018), along with lactate, lead to the calcification of tissue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on magnesium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-magnesium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-magnesium/</guid>
      <description>Parathyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role and Effects in Aging &#34;Phosphate, which predominates in grains, beans, nuts, meats, and fish, increases our production of parathyroid hormone, while calcium and magnesium inhibit its production. This hormone, which increases with age, suppresses immunity, and in excess it causes insomnia, seizures, dementia, psychosis, cancer, heart disease, respiratory distress and pulmonary hypertension, osteoporosis, sarcopenia, histamine release, inflammation and soft tissue calcification, and many other problems.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Mead Acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mead-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mead-acid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on meat</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-meat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-meat/</guid>
      <description>Nutrient Synergy in Diverse, Unrefined Foods Over Refined Meat &#34;Since all nutrients work together, its generally best to eat a variety of foods at each meal. Unrefined foods assure a fairly broad range of nutrients. People sometimes forget that meat is a refined food in this sense: it doesnt contain all the nutrients needed to make an animal.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote American Dietary Habits Leading to Bone and Tooth Deterioration &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on menopause</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-menopause/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-menopause/</guid>
      <description>Progesterone&amp;#39;s Role in Various Medical Conditions &#34;While progesterone might seem to cure almost everything, we should be careful to use it only when the biochemical mechanism is fairly evident. A progesterone deficiency can be misdiagnosed, as (for example) epilepsy, Brights disease, multiple sclerosis, or even estrogen deficiency (as in menopause). It can affect susceptibility to many conditions including herpes infections, dizziness, dysperception, varicose veins, mastitis, fibroma, and endometriosis. Cyclic edema, depression, and migraine are, in my experience, always stopped by progesterone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on metabolism</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Effect on Tryptophan Metabolism &#34;Estrogen strongly affects the metabolism of tryptophan, increasing its conversion to serotonin at the expense of niacinamide, which accounts for the symptoms of pellagra when the diet lacks tryptophan. When there’s enough protein in the diet, promotion of serotonin synthesis won’t result in a niacinamide deficiency, but conditions that increase the influence of estrogen will also increase the malfunctions involving serotonin.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Aerobic Glycolysis and Lactic Acid in Cancer Metabolism &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on microparticles</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-microparticles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-microparticles/</guid>
      <description>Environmental Factors Potentially Contributing to Autism &#34;Things in the environment, or substances produced in reactions to environmental stress, that might cause autism, include prenatal and neonatal exposure to radiation, including isotopes from the power industry, bomb testing, Chernobyl, and Fukushima; exposure to air pollution, including nitrogen oxides, ozone, carbon monoxide, sulfur dioxide, and particles (Jung, et al., 2013); aluminum (Mold, et al., 2018), lead, mercury, manganese, arsenic, cadmium, chromium, manganese, and nickel (Windham, et al, 2006); acetaminophen, infections, endotoxin, exogenous and endogenous estrogens, hypothyroidism, progesterone deficiency, agmatine deficiency, serotonin excess, endogenous nitric oxide (Sweeten, et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on milk</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-milk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-milk/</guid>
      <description>Milk&amp;#39;s Influence on Parathyroid Hormone and Optimal Levels &#34;Drinking milk lowers parathyroid hormone, relative to the diets that chronically stimulate its production. There has been very little attention given to the optimal level of parathyroid hormone, as opposed to the normal range.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Digestive Benefits and Protective Components of Milk &#34;its functions begin in the digestive system, with an instructive and supportive action, preparing the intestine’s defenses against the environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on mitochondria</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</guid>
      <description>Nutrient Importance for Mitochondrial Function and Aging &#34;n old age, the walls of blood vessels tend to become hardened with calcium. In at least some tissues, it is known that calcification begins in degenerating mitochondria, and mitochondria tend to deteriorate in aging tissue. Nutrients such as iodine, vitamin E, magnesium and vitamin B2 are especially important for maintaining the function of the mitochondria, which produce most of our energy.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nad plus</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on niacinamide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Effect on Tryptophan Metabolism &#34;Estrogen strongly affects the metabolism of tryptophan, increasing its conversion to serotonin at the expense of niacinamide, which accounts for the symptoms of pellagra when the diet lacks tryptophan. When there’s enough protein in the diet, promotion of serotonin synthesis won’t result in a niacinamide deficiency, but conditions that increase the influence of estrogen will also increase the malfunctions involving serotonin.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nutritional Therapy and Hormonal Support for Abnormal Pap Smears &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nitric oxide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</guid>
      <description>Spreading Damage Through Bystander Effects &#34;Severe stresses in one part of the body spread their influence through the body, in the process now called the bystander or off-target effect. Serotonin, nitric oxide, and ATP are among the substances that are known to spread damage&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Questioning Neodarwinism Through Hormetic Toxin Analysis &#34;If toxins such as CO and NO are beneficial, hormetically, when they occur in city air, then obviously they must be very beneficial when they are produced in the body by enzymes, which evolved through the natural selection of things that supported survival—there is a clear Panglossian aspect to neodarwinism, everything exists because of its fitness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on oxidation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</guid>
      <description>Commercial Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Oxidation Contamination Discovery &#34;About 40 years ago, someone noticed that the commercial cholesterol used for research was contaminated by oxidation, and that pure cholesterol didn’t produce the same toxic effects.&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Lipofuscin&amp;#39;s Role in Plaque Inflammation and Calcification &#34;The age pigment, ceroid or lipofuscin, that’s derived largely from PUFA and associated with the macrophage foam cells in the plaque, accumulates iron (Lee, et al, 1998), and by catalyzing oxidation, creates local hypoxia, leading to lactic acid production, contributing to an inflammatory process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on parathyroid hormone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</guid>
      <description>Parathyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role and Effects in Aging &#34;Phosphate, which predominates in grains, beans, nuts, meats, and fish, increases our production of parathyroid hormone, while calcium and magnesium inhibit its production. This hormone, which increases with age, suppresses immunity, and in excess it causes insomnia, seizures, dementia, psychosis, cancer, heart disease, respiratory distress and pulmonary hypertension, osteoporosis, sarcopenia, histamine release, inflammation and soft tissue calcification, and many other problems.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on potassium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-potassium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-potassium/</guid>
      <description>Stress Management Through Nutritional and Environmental Correction &#34;In general, stress should be met first by correcting the defect, which may be environmental or nutritional. Increased nutritional needs usually include protein and fat; acute hypoglycemia may require a large amount of sugar, and this suggests that the adrenals may be depleted, in which case pantothenic acid, vitamin C, vitamin A, magnesium and potassium should be provided in addition to other nutrients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pre-eclampsia</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pre-eclampsia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pre-eclampsia/</guid>
      <description>PMS, Edema, and Historical Treatments &#34;In PMS, edema is a common problem, and it used to be thought that edema of the brain was responsible for the irritability or depression or other nervous symptoms, and diuretics such es ammonium compounds and urea were commonly used. (Premenstrual salt cravings are the result of the estrogen-disturbed water balance, and salt-restriction for PMS is as inappropriate as it is for pre-eclampsia or toxemia of pregnancy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnancy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnancy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnancy/</guid>
      <description>Biological Water Retention and Cell Energy Relations &#34;The retention of water by the living substance is a topic that reductionist biology has been reluctant to discuss. There are no pumps for biological water, and it took a long time for a water channel protein to be proposed. The structural molecules of a cell, its metabolites and water are mutually dissolved, and their affinity for each other is affected by the cell’s energetic relation to its environment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnenolone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</guid>
      <description>Reversing Liver Degradation through Diet &#34;A lifetime of accumulating PUFA progressively degrades the liver’s protective functions, but those functions can gradually be restored by providing carbohydrates and saturated fats without the polyunsaturated fats, along with some of the factors that have been depleted along with free cholesterol, especially pregnenolone and progesterone.&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Progesterone Therapy for Male Infertility and Athlete’s Infertility &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on progesterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</guid>
      <description>SSRIs, Serotonin Myths, and Brain Allopregnanolone Synthesis &#34;Because it hasn’t been possible to provide evidence to support the idea that serotonin is a mood elevator happy hormone, the industry has looked for some way to explain the therapeutic benefit that they claim. They have generally settled on the idea that the SSRIs, after several weeks of use, increase the synthesis of the progesterone metabolite allopregnanolone, in the brain. That does happen, but the synthesis of those defensive steroids is also increased by any injury to the brain&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prolactin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen, Serotonin, and Water Retention Cycle &#34;Estrogen increases the formation of serotonin, and both of these substances increase the formation of prolactin, and activate the renin-angiotensin system, and increase secretion of the antidiuretic hormone vasopressin, all of which synergize with estrogen in promoting water retention. Serotonin increases the formation of estrogen, so a vicious circle can easily develop when the organism is under stress.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Serotonin, Estrogen, and Pituitary Hormones Promotion &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prostaglandins</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prostaglandins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prostaglandins/</guid>
      <description>Parathyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Effect on Hair Loss and Mast Cells &#34;In vitro experiments with hair follicles show that parathyroid hormone ends the growth cycle. Prostaglandin D2, associated with hair loss, is released from mast cells, and parathyroid hormone is an activator of mast cell degranulation. Hair growth has a 24 hour cycle, and the long cycle of hair shedding and renewal seems to be regulated by the genes involved in the daily cycle (Lin, et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prostate cancer</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prostate-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prostate-cancer/</guid>
      <description>Seasonal Variations in Breast Cancer Diagnoses &#34;There is a clear seasonality in the diagnosis (occurrence) of breast cancer, with a maximum in the spring and a minimum in the fall (Cohen, et al., 1983). The increased discovery in the spring coincides with rising gonadotropins (which are associated with breast and prostate cancer), and the decreased discovery in the fall coincides with higher vitamin D and lower stress hormones.&#34;
- May 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protective inhibition</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</guid>
      <description>The Oppositional Dynamics Between Estrogen and Progesterone and Their Biochemical Interactions &#34;This polar opposition of estrogen and progesterone also involves the polar antagonism of cyclic AMP and cyclic GMP, and to some extent a related antagonism of various prostaglandins (it has been suggested that this involves different populations of lysosomes, but I suspect it has to do with the superoxide dismutase enzyme system, and its inhibition or activation, since one of my assays to determine the action of estrogen turns out to be an inverse indicator of S.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protein</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protein/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protein/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Effect on Tryptophan Metabolism &#34;Estrogen strongly affects the metabolism of tryptophan, increasing its conversion to serotonin at the expense of niacinamide, which accounts for the symptoms of pellagra when the diet lacks tryptophan. When there’s enough protein in the diet, promotion of serotonin synthesis won’t result in a niacinamide deficiency, but conditions that increase the influence of estrogen will also increase the malfunctions involving serotonin.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Biological Water Retention and Cell Energy Relations &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on PUFAs</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</guid>
      <description>Lipid Peroxidation in Atherosclerotic Plaques&amp;#39; Impact &#34;Lipid peroxidation was observed in atherosclerotic plaques, and the breakdown products of polyunsaturated fats such as hydroxynonenal, malondialdehyde, and acrolein (from EPA, arachidonic acid, and other highly unsaturated fats in the affected blood vessel are known to attract white blood cells such as macrophages, which accumulate in the plaques.&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Lipofuscin&amp;#39;s Role in Plaque Inflammation and Calcification &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on red light</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-red-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-red-light/</guid>
      <description>Polanyi&amp;#39;s Adsorption Potential and Atomistic View Challenges &#34;it is now clear that Polanyis adsorption potential was a fact, and Einstein and Haber were dogmatically wrong in their ideas about inter-atomic forces. Seeing this, we should question the many consequences of the same mistaken atomistic view, including Einsteins theory of photoelectricity, which attributed a corpuscular quality to light, because he knew that matter was strictly particulate without any of the long-range energy properties that were later demonstrated by Polanyi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on salt and sodium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-salt-and-sodium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-salt-and-sodium/</guid>
      <description>Body&amp;#39;s Adjustment Period to Increased Sodium Intake &#34;If you suddenly increase your sodium intake, your body will take a day or two to adjust, and during that time you will retain a little extra water, but after the short adjustment time, you lose sodium at the same rate that you take it in.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Estrogen&amp;#39;s Influence on Water Retention and Salt Cravings &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on science</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</guid>
      <description>Commercial Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Oxidation Contamination Discovery &#34;About 40 years ago, someone noticed that the commercial cholesterol used for research was contaminated by oxidation, and that pure cholesterol didn’t produce the same toxic effects.&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Reductionism&amp;#39;s Denial of Objective Generalization in Science &#34;The dominant reductionist philosophy of science denies that generalization is an objective process, and has strenuously attacked the idea that intention or purpose guides biological, biochemical and genetic changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on selenium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on serotonin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Effect on Tryptophan Metabolism &#34;Estrogen strongly affects the metabolism of tryptophan, increasing its conversion to serotonin at the expense of niacinamide, which accounts for the symptoms of pellagra when the diet lacks tryptophan. When there’s enough protein in the diet, promotion of serotonin synthesis won’t result in a niacinamide deficiency, but conditions that increase the influence of estrogen will also increase the malfunctions involving serotonin.&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Estrogen, Serotonin, and Water Retention Cycle &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sleep</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sleep/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Gland Recovery and Function Post Supplementation &#34;Contrary to popular ideas about thyroid, the gland will resume its functioning after stopping the use of a supplement even if it has been suppressed, and sometimes taking thyroid will increase the glands function to normal. Taking thyroid will sometimes help thin people gain weight, by improving protein metabolism, and it often helps people to sleep more soundly.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Magnesium Carbonate&amp;#39;s Potential to Improve Sleep Quality &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sugar</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</guid>
      <description>Aerobic Glycolysis and Lactic Acid in Cancer Metabolism &#34;Aerobic glycolysis, the metabolism characteristic of cancer, in which lactic acid is produced from glucose despite the presence of oxygen, is promoted by serotonin&#34;
- September 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Substance-Induced Brain Growth and Efficient Energy Use &#34;-progesterone, glucose, or glycine which was converted into glucose (Zamenhof and Ahmad, 1979)—increased brain growth, by increasing either the supply of energy or the ability to use energy effectively&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on testosterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</guid>
      <description>Testosterone&amp;#39;s Stability and Lack of Adaptiveness in Males &#34;The primary male hormone, testosterone, has chemical and functional properties of both estrogen and progesterone; this combined function gives males a short-term stability (fewer goiters, migraines, etc.) but a lack of adaptiveness in the longer range (higher mortality in infancy and old age).&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Substances Opposing Estrogen in Cancer Therapy &#34;Anything which produces tissue atrophy will tend to produce cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the brain</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>BBB and Cellular Stress: Evidence in Blood &#34;The Blood Brain Barrier, BBB, has sometimes been treated as something unique, but it’s just a special case of the cellular resistance that exists everywhere. For example, after intense exercise that produces fatigue and damage to muscles, a unique brain protein, S100B, that is considered a crucial part of the BBB, can be found in the blood stream. The exchange of substances, even proteins and nucleic acids, between cells and their environment, increases during stress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the heart</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</guid>
      <description>Hypothyroidism Effects on Muscle Fatigue and Metabolites &#34;When metabolic energy is failing, as in hypothyroidism, muscles become easily fatigued, and take up excess water, and the barrier structure is loosened, allowing macromolecules and ATP and other metabolites to leak out, while extraneous substances enter. Typical muscle enzymes such as lactate dehydrogenase and creatine kinase appear in the bloodstream in typical hypothyroid myopathy, and heart proteins, including a particular form of lactic dehydrogenase and a muscle protein, troponin, appear in the blood after a heart stress or fatigue combined with hypothyroidism or systemic inflammation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the immune system</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</guid>
      <description>Bodily Experiences Influencing Vitality and Physiology &#34;Our bodies are constantly having experiences, and generalizing from them in the way they respond; these generalized responses can limit or expand our vitality. These generalizations are expressed in our anatomy, physiology, and ecosystems, with changes in immunity, metabolism, gene expression, and behavior.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Parathyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role and Effects in Aging &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the liver</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</guid>
      <description>Liver&amp;#39;s Response to Lack of Polyunsaturated Fats &#34;When the diet lacks the polyunsaturated fatty acids, the liver synthesizes saturated fatty acids, and exports its cholesterol mainly in combination with palmitate, which doesn’t promote lipid peroxidation, or in the non-esterified free form.&#34;
- September 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Reversing Liver Degradation through Diet &#34;A lifetime of accumulating PUFA progressively degrades the liver’s protective functions, but those functions can gradually be restored by providing carbohydrates and saturated fats without the polyunsaturated fats, along with some of the factors that have been depleted along with free cholesterol, especially pregnenolone and progesterone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on thyroid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</guid>
      <description>The Costly Adaptations of Serotonin Production &#34;Stresses of different sorts increase the formation of serotonin and the various pituitary hormones, leading to adaptive changes in the organism, but at the cost of causing inflammation and degeneration. Studies of several of the pituitary hormones have shown age-accelerating effects, leading to edema, inflammation, fibrosis, and decreased longevity. W.D. Denckla’s experiments showing the great life extending effect of removing the pituitary gland, while supplementing thyroid and glucocorticoid hormones, suggest the possibilities inherent in finding ways to prevent the over-production of serotonin and its associated hormones and cytokines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on urea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-urea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-urea/</guid>
      <description>Urea&amp;#39;s Decline in Treating Brain Injury &#34;As recently as the 1950s urea was recognized as the most effective treatment for brain swelling, but the science based membrane theory reasoned that the removal of water from cells was always governed by osmosis, and since urea could remove water from cells, it must be osmotically active. As an osmolyte, it was added to distilled water for intravenous use, and the red blood cells behaved as they would in distilled water, dissolving.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin A</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-a/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone and Vitamin A Against Estrogen&amp;#39;s Effects &#34;Thyroid hormone and Vitamin A promote protein metabolism and antagonize some of estrogens effects. In fact, hyperthyroidism is known to be able to cause estrogen levels to fall below normal.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Zinc, Vitamin A, and Blood Sugar Impact on Herpes &#34;Zinc and vitamin A may also act through the blood sugar. It is well known that an emotional upset, spending too much time in the sun, working too long without eating, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin B1</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b1/</guid>
      <description> Vitamin B1&amp;#39;s Rapid Impact on Irritability and Mental Clarity &#34;A peculiar kind of irritability, sometimes with a sense of having your head in a kind of cloud, is often a result of a vitamin B1 deficiency. If that is the cause, it will clear up within a few minutes after taking the vitamin. Magnesium deficiency is another common cause of irritability.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin B2</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b2/</guid>
      <description>Nutritional and Hormonal Impacts on Cellular Respiration &#34;Various nutritional, hormonal, or toxic states interfere with respiration in different ways: for example, vitamin E deficiency, estrogen excess, toxic thyroid, and DNP (the formerly popular cancer-causing reducing drug) cause oxygen to be consumed without producing the normal amount of useful energy. Vitamin B2 or copper deficiency can prevent consumption of oxygen. Cancer (contrary to a tenacious establishment doctrine) involves a respiratory defect, and causes a tendency toward hypoglycemia which is often compensated by the conversion of protein to sugar, leading to the terminal wasting state (cachexia)&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin B5</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b5/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b5/</guid>
      <description>Stress Management Through Nutritional and Environmental Correction &#34;In general, stress should be met first by correcting the defect, which may be environmental or nutritional. Increased nutritional needs usually include protein and fat; acute hypoglycemia may require a large amount of sugar, and this suggests that the adrenals may be depleted, in which case pantothenic acid, vitamin C, vitamin A, magnesium and potassium should be provided in addition to other nutrients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin B6</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-b6/</guid>
      <description>The Long-term Pancreatic Damage Due to Malnutrition and Deficiencies &#34;The pancreas can be damaged by prolonged malnutrition, so that the inability to produce insulin may be permanent. Magnesium and vitamin B6 deficiencies are known to be involved in damage to the pancreas. Insulin itself is only part of the insulin-like system (Adv in Metabol Disorders 7, p.26, 1974); proper treatment requires a proper study of all factors.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nutritional Relief for Copper or Estrogen Induced Tension &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin D</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-d/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-d/</guid>
      <description>Effects of Parathyroid Hormone Increase on Body Tissues &#34;When vitamin D or calcium is deficient, or when phosphate is excessive, and in hypoglycemia and stress (Ljunghall, et al., 1984), parathyroid hormone increases. This can lead to softening of bones, and hardening of soft tissues, especially arteries, sometimes brain, skin and other organs. Parathyroid hormone increases blood pressure, even before the calcium stiffening is detected.&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin E</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-e/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-e/</guid>
      <description>Substances Opposing Estrogen in Cancer Therapy &#34;Anything which produces tissue atrophy will tend to produce cancer. The important question is, what will induce differentiation and useful function in cancer cells? There are many substances which promote differentiation and oppose the effects of estrogen, and some of these have been found to be useful in cancer therapy. Among the substances opposing estrogen are dopamine and nickel, prolactin inhibitors; chalones, the tissue specific proteins which inhibit cell division (and possibly more ephemerally, the peptides of memory); the aprotic solvents, DMF and possibly DMSO; progesterone and testosterone; thyroxin and iodine; magnesium ATP, the stable form of the biological energy molecule; vitamin A, a protein-sparing nutrient which promotes differentiation, and vitamin E (and the closely related coenzyme Q, or ubiquinone).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin K</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-k/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-k/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on zinc</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</guid>
      <description>Nutritional Relief for Copper or Estrogen Induced Tension &#34;Tension resulting from too much copper or estrogen can be relieved nutritionally. Usually a zinc supplement is necessary — about 20 mg. a day; about 30 mg. of vitamin B6 has been recommended for this problem, but the amount varies with the individual. The other B vitamins, and vitamins E and A should also be used.&#34;
- Nutrition For Women Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nutrient Needs in Stress Resistance and Recovery &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
