<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ray Peat Explained</title>
    <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ray Peat Explained</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raypeatexplained.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on adaptation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</guid>
      <description>Intestinal Stress Effects Overlooked &#34;While the effects of stress on the intestine have been recognized since Hans Selye described the general adaptation syndrome (with intestinal bleeding as an early sign of stress), that hasnt been taken into account in any of the large brain trauma or stroke studies.&#34;
- March 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aspirin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</guid>
      <description>Aspirin&amp;#39;s Increased Vitamin K Requirement &#34;aspirin makes you need more vitamin K, even when you arent using much. People who use aspirin for arthritis or cancer often take several grams a day.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Reducing Aspirin&amp;#39;s Stomach Reactions &#34;I dont know anyone who has a stomach reaction when they dissolve the aspirin in hot water, and then take it with food.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ATP</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid&amp;#39;s Impact on Caloric Needs and Glucose Regulation &#34;In my teens and twenties, I needed about 8000 calories per day when I was physically active, about 4000 to 5000 when I was sedentary, but after I took thyroid, I needed only about half as many calories. Thyroid is the basic regulator of blood glucose, and it causes it to be fully oxidized for energy, so that it produces ATP efficiently, on relatively few calories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on biological energy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Balancing Calorie Intake with Physical Activity Levels &#34;often ate more than 5000 calories, but when Im completely sedentary for more than ten hours daily, my energy requirement is much lower. The calorie intake should be balanced to your heat production and activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ciproheptadine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on copper</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</guid>
      <description>Copper Solution&amp;#39;s Immediate Effects on Hair Pigmentation &#34;I found that applying a weak solution of copper just once would restore color immediately to eyebrows, or to about 10% of sideburn hairs,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cortisol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</guid>
      <description>Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;Pregnenolone isnt a hormone, but it normalizes the steroid hormones, preventing excess cortisol and helping to normalize aldosterone, so it should be helpful for any stress including surgery. P&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Blood Glucose&amp;#39;s Role in Cortisone Formation &#34;the basic signal which causes cortisone to be formed is a drop in the blood glucose level. The increased energy requirement of any stress tends to cause the blood sugar to fall slightly, but hypothyroidism itself tends to depress blood sugar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dhea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
The Foundational Role of Progesterone and DHEA &#34;Progesterone and DHEA are the precursors for the other more specialized steroid hormones, including cortisol, aldosterone (sodium-retaining hormone), estrogen, and testosterone.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on digestion</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</guid>
      <description>Intestinal Irritation Link to Tinnitus Through Endotoxin &#34;anything that irritates the intestine can cause tinnitus by increasing endotoxin absorption.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Intestinal Stress Effects Overlooked &#34;While the effects of stress on the intestine have been recognized since Hans Selye described the general adaptation syndrome (with intestinal bleeding as an early sign of stress), that hasnt been taken into account in any of the large brain trauma or stroke studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dopamine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</guid>
      <description> Dopamine&amp;#39;s Role in Toxin Production within Substantia Nigra &#34;The high local concentration of dopamine in the substantial negra, reacting with iron, produces a variety of toxins&#34;
- March 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on estrogen</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</guid>
      <description>Endorphins&amp;#39; Possible Role in Ovarian Cancer Symptoms &#34;I think excess endorphins are often the problem, and the antagonist can sometimes be helpful. The endorphins differ in their effects on the two sides of the body, so when I knew two women (within the same year) who had been having mysterious one-sided symptoms for a few months before discovering that they had ovarian cancer (on the same side), I thought that the endorphins were probably involved, maybe to suppress pain on that side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on gaba</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Gilbert Ling</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Hans Selye</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on inflammation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</guid>
      <description>Regenerative Processes: The Enzymatic Pathways Triggered by Injury &#34;In the first reactions to injury, the inflammatory changes activate enzymes that support undifferentiated growth.&#34;
- July 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Brain-Inflammation Link to Organs &#34;The inflammatory, degenerative processes in the brain take a few hours to develop, and during these few hours the stress signals from the brain are causing changes in the intestine that lead to a systemic inflammatory state&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on lactic acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Reductive Stress and Its Self-Reinforcing Biochemical Cycles &#34;he reductive state, resulting from starvation or hypoglycemia, or an excess of lactate or fat, or oxygen deprivation, activates the release of glutamate, and the excitation produced by that can shut off mitochondrial oxidation, reinforcing the state of pseudohypoxia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on metabolism</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen, Injury, and Energy Metabolism &#34;The remarkable fact that both estrogen and nitric oxide are produced by practically any injury has seldom been mentioned, and their closely related effects on energy metabolism have been generally ignored.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Estrogen&amp;#39;s Disruption of Oxidative Metabolism for Reproduction and Repair &#34;A substance such as estrogen is able to interrupt oxidative metabolism to initiate reproduction of the organism, or to stimulate tissue repair, in response to a local injury.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on mitochondria</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</guid>
      <description> Deterioration of Animal Mitochondria in Darkness &#34;In animal experiments, it was found that their mitochondria progressively deteriorated during the hours of darkness.&#34;
- March 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nad plus</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on niacinamide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nitric oxide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</guid>
      <description>Daily Skin Washing Disrupts Endocrine Function &#34;Just washing the skin with pure soap alters the skins endocrine function for days. and doing it every day is an endocrine disrupter, even if there are no toxic additives in the soap.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Cortisone&amp;#39;s Limitations Without Addressing Underlying Causes &#34;Although cortisone supplementation can help in a great variety of stress-related diseases, no cure will take place unless the basic cause is discovered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on oxidation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Disruption of Oxidative Metabolism for Reproduction and Repair &#34;A substance such as estrogen is able to interrupt oxidative metabolism to initiate reproduction of the organism, or to stimulate tissue repair, in response to a local injury.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Metabolic Shifts from Glucose to Fat and Its Consequences &#34;The shift of metabolic fuel from glucose to fat causes the oxidation state of the organism to shift to the reduced side, away from the oxidized state which favors stable differentiated functioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on parathyroid hormone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</guid>
      <description>Nighttime Parathyroid Hormone Activity and Calcium Loss &#34;During the night, parathyroid hormone usually rises (Radjaipour 1986; Logue 1989, 1990; Fraser, 1998), and especially during aging, this causes a significant loss of calcium from the bones. Having a large part of the day’s calcium at bedtime reduces the nocturnal rise of PTH and calcium loss from bones&#34;
- September 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnenolone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Concerns Over Administering DHEA Without Balanced Hormones &#34;Since DHEA can be easily metabolized into testosterone (by the skin, for example), and into estrogen, I dont think it should ever be administered alone, without an approximately natural balance of pregnenolone and progesterone.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on progesterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Progesterone&amp;#39;s Non-Suppressive Effect on Its Synthesis &#34;The fact that progesterone (and probably pregnenolone) stimulates its own synthesis means that taking it does not suppress the bodys ability to synthesize it, as happens with cortisol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prolactin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protective inhibition</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</guid>
      <description>Understanding Sleep Onset through Cortical Inhibition &#34;The familiar events at the onset of sleep can be understood in terms of the spread of inhibition from the cortex to the brainstem and adjoining structures.&#34;
- March 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Structured Nature of Stimulation and Resulting Inhibition &#34;Stimulation and excitation always have a particular structure, according to the perceived meaning, and for Pavlov, the resulting inhibition was also structured.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on PUFAs</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</guid>
      <description>Quick Recovery from Stress with Low PUFA &#34;a person relatively free of PUFA will be likely to recover very quickly from prolonged stress.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Factors Disrupting Respiratory Enzyme and PUFA Balance &#34;tamin E deficiency or PUFA excess, by ionizing radiation, by oxygen deprivation, or by aging. All of these conditions involved interference with, or decreased activity of, the crucial respiratory enzyme, cytochrome C oxidase.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on science</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</guid>
      <description>Time&amp;#39;s Perception: Mainstream Science vs. Antireductionist Views &#34;The understanding of time is where there is the most radical difference between mainstream philosophy of science and the antireductionist dissenters.&#34;
- January 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Depersonalization in Scientific Writing: A Propaganda Technique &#34;The style of writing in science journals is explicitly intended to depersonalize language, to give the impression of objectivity. That is a propaganda technique, that contributes nothing to scientific objectivity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on selenium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on serotonin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</guid>
      <description>Environmental Factors Potentially Contributing to Autism &#34;Things in the environment, or substances produced in reactions to environmental stress, that might cause autism, include prenatal and neonatal exposure to radiation, including isotopes from the power industry, bomb testing, Chernobyl, and Fukushima; exposure to air pollution, including nitrogen oxides, ozone, carbon monoxide, sulfur dioxide, and particles (Jung, et al., 2013); aluminum (Mold, et al., 2018), lead, mercury, manganese, arsenic, cadmium, chromium, manganese, and nickel (Windham, et al, 2006); acetaminophen, infections, endotoxin, exogenous and endogenous estrogens, hypothyroidism, progesterone deficiency, agmatine deficiency, serotonin excess, endogenous nitric oxide (Sweeten, et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sugar</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Starch&amp;#39;s Nutritional Impact Compared to Sugar &#34;When starch is well cooked, and eaten with some fat and the essential nutrients, its safe, except that its more likely than sugar to produce fat, and isnt as effective for mineral balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on testosterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</guid>
      <description>Concerns Over Administering DHEA Without Balanced Hormones &#34;Since DHEA can be easily metabolized into testosterone (by the skin, for example), and into estrogen, I dont think it should ever be administered alone, without an approximately natural balance of pregnenolone and progesterone.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Testosterone Decline and Estrogen Increase Due to Stress &#34;Men’s testosterone declines with stress and aging, and its conversion to estrogen is increased by stress and inflammation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the brain</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the heart</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</guid>
      <description>Stress-Related Cortisone&amp;#39;s Role in Heart Attacks &#34;According to Meerson, heart attacks are provoked and aggravated by the cortisone produced during stress. (Meerson and his colleagues have demonstrated that the progress of a heart attack can be halted by a treatment including natural substances such as vitamin E and magnesium.)&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Nitric Oxide&amp;#39;s Indirect Heart Activity via Parasympathetics &#34;Nitric oxide has an action on the heart that isnt directly related to the blood vessels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the immune system</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</guid>
      <description>Metchnikoff and Beyond: The Immune System&amp;#39;s Harmony with the Microbiome &#34;The embryologist Elie Metchnikoff looked at immunity as an aspect of the organism’s maintenance of its own integrity.&#34;
- November 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Cultural Acceptance of Suffering as Strengthening Practice &#34;Looking at the larger culture of western civilization, mortification of the flesh for the good of the soul might be a relevant context for these persistent attitudes in medicine and biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the liver</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Thyroid Gland&amp;#39;s Secretion Ratio, Liver&amp;#39;s Role in Conversion &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on thyroid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</guid>
      <description>Contextualizing the Unphysiological Dosing of T3 Hormone &#34;Since the body normally produces about 4 mcg of T3 in an hour, taking 10 or 20 mcg at once is unphysiological.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on zinc</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
