<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ray Peat Explained</title>
    <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ray Peat Explained</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raypeatexplained.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on adaptation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</guid>
      <description>Harsh Environments: Early Reproduction and Energy Adaptation &#34;The stresses of a harsh environment that make early reproduction advantageous, or that require accelerated tissue renewal, also favor epigenetic adaptations that reduce energy demands.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.pdf
Epigenetic Changes from Stress Adaptation &#34;In all of these conditions of stress adaptation, epigenetic modifications of DNA are involved, with nitric oxide participating, with estrogen and other hormones, in methylation of DNA and modification of histones, and a variety of other biochemical lingering modifications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aspirin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</guid>
      <description>Aspirin&amp;#39;s Increased Vitamin K Requirement &#34;aspirin makes you need more vitamin K, even when you arent using much. People who use aspirin for arthritis or cancer often take several grams a day.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Germicidal Properties of Aspirin &#34;Aspirin has a mild germicidal effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Reducing Aspirin&amp;#39;s Stomach Reactions &#34;I dont know anyone who has a stomach reaction when they dissolve the aspirin in hot water, and then take it with food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on biological energy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Balancing Calorie Intake with Physical Activity Levels &#34;often ate more than 5000 calories, but when Im completely sedentary for more than ten hours daily, my energy requirement is much lower. The calorie intake should be balanced to your heat production and activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on copper</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</guid>
      <description>Copper Solution&amp;#39;s Immediate Effects on Hair Pigmentation &#34;I found that applying a weak solution of copper just once would restore color immediately to eyebrows, or to about 10% of sideburn hairs,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cortisol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</guid>
      <description>Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;Pregnenolone isnt a hormone, but it normalizes the steroid hormones, preventing excess cortisol and helping to normalize aldosterone, so it should be helpful for any stress including surgery. P&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Fatty Acids Stimulate Hormone Production &#34;The unsaturated fatty acids increase activation of the pituitary and adrenal cortex, increasing the production of ACTH and the glucocorticoids&#34;
- January 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dhea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Protective Roles of Progesterone During High-Energy States &#34;during constructive exploration, energy is abundant, and cells with the highest energy needs are protected by progesterone, testosterone, DHEA, and other steroids.&#34;
- January 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dopamine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</guid>
      <description>Exploring Sensory Experience Modification in Parkinson&amp;#39;s Therapy &#34;Without knowing the basic causes of Parkinson’s disease (and it isn’t very helpful to keep hearing that it’s caused by the death of dopaminergic cells in the substantial nigra), we don’t know how much can be achieved by way of modifying sensory experience, but if we consider the powerful biological effects of learned helpless, and the simplicity with which it can be alleviated, we can imagine that the therapeutic possibilities in that direction might be great.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on estrogen</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</guid>
      <description>Endorphins&amp;#39; Possible Role in Ovarian Cancer Symptoms &#34;I think excess endorphins are often the problem, and the antagonist can sometimes be helpful. The endorphins differ in their effects on the two sides of the body, so when I knew two women (within the same year) who had been having mysterious one-sided symptoms for a few months before discovering that they had ovarian cancer (on the same side), I thought that the endorphins were probably involved, maybe to suppress pain on that side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on gaba</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Gilbert Ling</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Hans Selye</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on inflammation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</guid>
      <description>Rethinking Nitric Oxide&amp;#39;s Role in Cellular Stress &#34;If we called nitric oxide an anti-respiratory pro-inflammatory substance produced mostly by stressed cells, we would be very cautious about medical techniques to increase its production.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.pdf
Regenerative Processes: The Enzymatic Pathways Triggered by Injury &#34;In the first reactions to injury, the inflammatory changes activate enzymes that support undifferentiated growth.&#34;
- July 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter_2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on lactic acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.pdf
Extreme Stress and Biological Adaptation: Survival&amp;#39;s Tightrope &#34;During adaptation, the functional load is shifted to the system that is meeting the new challenge, and a variety of stimuli, from nerves and hormones, activate the cells of that responsive system, and resources, such as amino acids, can be moved from less active systems to support the new level of functioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on metabolism</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Estrogen, Injury, and Energy Metabolism &#34;The remarkable fact that both estrogen and nitric oxide are produced by practically any injury has seldom been mentioned, and their closely related effects on energy metabolism have been generally ignored.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nad plus</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.pdf
Hypothyroidism and the Risk of Reductive Stress &#34;The weak oxidative metabolism in hypothyroidism makes it easy to enter a state of reductive stress, with a shift toward a higher concentration of NADH and lactate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nitric oxide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</guid>
      <description>Daily Skin Washing Disrupts Endocrine Function &#34;Just washing the skin with pure soap alters the skins endocrine function for days. and doing it every day is an endocrine disrupter, even if there are no toxic additives in the soap.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Oxygen Levels in Venous Blood During Shock &#34;venous blood in shock is likely to be bright red, showing that no oxygen was extracted by the tissues.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on oxidation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Influence on Cellular Metabolism and Differentiation &#34;1 interpreted estrogens role in reproduction and cell proliferation in terms of an idea that was discussed by Otto Warburg and others. In this view, multiplication is the basic, simplest function of any cell, and it is supported by inefficient non-oxidative metabolism, while the differentiation of cells to form part of a stable multicellular organism requires the highly efficient oxidativ&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on parathyroid hormone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</guid>
      <description>Complex Mechanisms in Pseudohypoxic State Perpetuation &#34;There are several important mechanisms that are involved in perpetuating a pseudohypoxic state, and they can operate in a single tissue or organ, as well as in a generalized way throughout the organism. The thing that is often overlooked is the coherent overlapping interaction of the structural sulfhydryl redox system (-SH, -SS-), the redox regulation of gene expression, the glycolytic and oxidative energy metabolisms, regulation of pH and ionic selectivity, osmolarity, and solvent properties, especially the hydroephobic/hydrophilic balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnenolone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Indirect Role in Hormonal Balance and Stress &#34;Pregnenolone doesnt have the direct hormonal effects, but its the precursor, and by stopping exaggerated stress reactions it is likely to help&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on progesterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Progesterone&amp;#39;s Potential Anticancer Properties Underexplored &#34;Progesterone has a wide spectrum of anticancer activity, but as far as I know only synthetic progestins have been used medically. Although I used myself it on things that appeared to be very active melanomas, I usually recommend a slightly hyperthyroid state for helping to control it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prolactin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protective inhibition</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</guid>
      <description>Nitric Oxide: Central Factor in Shock State Dynamics &#34;nitric oxide was a central factor in the shock state, and that inhibiting its formation could alleviate the shock state. The state of shock was often called circulatory failure, from excessive vasodilation, s0 it was easy to see a role for the vasodilator nitric oxide in circulatory collapse;&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter.pdf
Estrogen-Induced Anti-Respiratory Substances and Their Effects &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on selenium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on serotonin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</guid>
      <description>Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer. It also has calcium blocking action, aldosterone antagonism, and antagonizes serotonins antidiuretic effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;The imbalances of endorphins, serotonin, catecholamines, and other nerve-regulators that have been seen in autism sometimes can be produced in adults by combined fatigue and poor nutrition, and when the livers glycogen is depleted, it can be hard to restore the balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sugar</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Starch&amp;#39;s Nutritional Impact Compared to Sugar &#34;When starch is well cooked, and eaten with some fat and the essential nutrients, its safe, except that its more likely than sugar to produce fat, and isnt as effective for mineral balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the brain</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the immune system</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</guid>
      <description>Historical Perspectives on Autoimmune Disease Treatment &#34;The idea of autoimmune disease can be traced back to Paul Ehrlich’s theory of immunity, and his idea of a therapeutic magic bullet has dominated the medical approach to treating the autoimmune diseases.&#34;
- November 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter .pdf
Metchnikoff and Beyond: The Immune System&amp;#39;s Harmony with the Microbiome &#34;The embryologist Elie Metchnikoff looked at immunity as an aspect of the organism’s maintenance of its own integrity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the liver</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on thyroid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</guid>
      <description>Contextualizing the Unphysiological Dosing of T3 Hormone &#34;Since the body normally produces about 4 mcg of T3 in an hour, taking 10 or 20 mcg at once is unphysiological.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat.pdf
Thyroid as Primary Regulator of Respiratory Adaptation &#34;Thyroid is the main regulatory and adaptive substance for respiration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on zinc</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
