<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ray Peat Explained</title>
    <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ray Peat Explained</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raypeatexplained.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on adaptation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid as Primary Regulator of Respiratory Adaptation &#34;Thyroid is the main regulatory and adaptive substance for respiration.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Harmful Effects of Prolonged Cortisone During Stress &#34;Meersons work has revealed in a detailed way how the usually beneficial hormone of adaptation, cortisone, can cause so many other harmful effects when its action is too prolonged or too intense.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aspirin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</guid>
      <description>Aspirin&amp;#39;s Increased Vitamin K Requirement &#34;aspirin makes you need more vitamin K, even when you arent using much. People who use aspirin for arthritis or cancer often take several grams a day.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Germicidal Properties of Aspirin &#34;Aspirin has a mild germicidal effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Reducing Aspirin&amp;#39;s Stomach Reactions &#34;I dont know anyone who has a stomach reaction when they dissolve the aspirin in hot water, and then take it with food.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ATP</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid&amp;#39;s Impact on Caloric Needs and Glucose Regulation &#34;In my teens and twenties, I needed about 8000 calories per day when I was physically active, about 4000 to 5000 when I was sedentary, but after I took thyroid, I needed only about half as many calories. Thyroid is the basic regulator of blood glucose, and it causes it to be fully oxidized for energy, so that it produces ATP efficiently, on relatively few calories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on biological energy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Balancing Calorie Intake with Physical Activity Levels &#34;often ate more than 5000 calories, but when Im completely sedentary for more than ten hours daily, my energy requirement is much lower. The calorie intake should be balanced to your heat production and activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cholesterol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cholesterol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cholesterol/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Animal Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Conversion into Steroids, Role of Thyroid &#34;In animals, cholesterol is the basic sterol molecule, which is massively converted into other substances, including the steroid hormones. Thyroid hormone and vitamin A are required for this conversion.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ciproheptadine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</guid>
      <description> Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer. It also has calcium blocking action, aldosterone antagonism, and antagonizes serotonins antidiuretic effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on copper</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</guid>
      <description> Copper Solution&amp;#39;s Immediate Effects on Hair Pigmentation &#34;I found that applying a weak solution of copper just once would restore color immediately to eyebrows, or to about 10% of sideburn hairs,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cortisol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</guid>
      <description>Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;Pregnenolone isnt a hormone, but it normalizes the steroid hormones, preventing excess cortisol and helping to normalize aldosterone, so it should be helpful for any stress including surgery. P&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Progesterone&amp;#39;s Non-Suppressive Effect on Its Synthesis &#34;The fact that progesterone (and probably pregnenolone) stimulates its own synthesis means that taking it does not suppress the bodys ability to synthesize it, as happens with cortisol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on depression</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-depression/</guid>
      <description>Blood Glucose&amp;#39;s Role in Cortisone Formation &#34;the basic signal which causes cortisone to be formed is a drop in the blood glucose level. The increased energy requirement of any stress tends to cause the blood sugar to fall slightly, but hypothyroidism itself tends to depress blood sugar.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Lithium&amp;#39;s Treatment for Mood Disorders &#34;Lithium has been used for many years to treat various mood disorders, including anxiety and depression, and it reduces activation of the NMDA system, possibly by binding ammonia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dhea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes The Foundational Role of Progesterone and DHEA &#34;Progesterone and DHEA are the precursors for the other more specialized steroid hormones, including cortisol, aldosterone (sodium-retaining hormone), estrogen, and testosterone.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on digestion</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</guid>
      <description>Intestinal Irritation Link to Tinnitus Through Endotoxin &#34;anything that irritates the intestine can cause tinnitus by increasing endotoxin absorption.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Therapeutic Potentials of Carbon Dioxide Usage &#34;Direct use of carbon dioxide is likely to be helpful in all the situations that are known to be benefitted by acetazolamide, without the risk of allergy to that drug—traumatic brain edema, mountain sickness, osteoporosis, epilepsy, glaucoma, hyperactivity (ADHD), inflammation, polyps of the intestine, and arthritis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dopamine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</guid>
      <description>Exploring Sensory Experience Modification in Parkinson&amp;#39;s Therapy &#34;Without knowing the basic causes of Parkinson’s disease (and it isn’t very helpful to keep hearing that it’s caused by the death of dopaminergic cells in the substantial nigra), we don’t know how much can be achieved by way of modifying sensory experience, but if we consider the powerful biological effects of learned helpless, and the simplicity with which it can be alleviated, we can imagine that the therapeutic possibilities in that direction might be great.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on estrogen</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</guid>
      <description>Endorphins&amp;#39; Possible Role in Ovarian Cancer Symptoms &#34;I think excess endorphins are often the problem, and the antagonist can sometimes be helpful. The endorphins differ in their effects on the two sides of the body, so when I knew two women (within the same year) who had been having mysterious one-sided symptoms for a few months before discovering that they had ovarian cancer (on the same side), I thought that the endorphins were probably involved, maybe to suppress pain on that side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on gaba</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Gilbert Ling</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Hans Selye</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on inflammation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</guid>
      <description>Hypothyroidism&amp;#39;s Impact on Cortisone and Inflammation &#34;While hypothyroidism makes the body require more cortisone to sustain blood sugar and energy production, it also limits the ability to produce cortisone, so in some cases stress produces symptoms resulting from a deficiency of cortisone, including various forms of arthritis and more generalized types of chronic inflammation.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Rethinking Nitric Oxide&amp;#39;s Role in Cellular Stress &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on lactic acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Extreme Stress and Biological Adaptation: Survival&amp;#39;s Tightrope &#34;During adaptation, the functional load is shifted to the system that is meeting the new challenge, and a variety of stimuli, from nerves and hormones, activate the cells of that responsive system, and resources, such as amino acids, can be moved from less active systems to support the new level of functioning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on metabolism</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Steroid Hormones&amp;#39; Integral Role in Animal Physiology &#34;The steroid hormones are involved in all aspects of animal physiology, and overlap with control functions of the nervous system, peptide hormones, metabolites, prostaglandins, cyclic nucleotides, etc&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on microparticles</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-microparticles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-microparticles/</guid>
      <description>Misinterpreted Studies on Vitamin E&amp;#39;s Effects in JAMA &#34;Around 1980, a friend showed me an article in JAMA that warned about the dangers of vitamin E, with many citations of research publications. Most of the articles that the author said showed the harmful effects of vitamin E were actually reporting biological changes that the researchers considered to be beneficial.&#34;
- July 2018 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Microscopic Food Particles in Blood and Urine &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on mitochondria</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</guid>
      <description>Nitric Oxide&amp;#39;s Overlooked Mitochondrial Oxygen Inhibition &#34;Only an extremely small minority of publications on the physiology of nitric oxide are concerned with the fact that it inhibits mitochondrial use of oxygen for energy production&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Estrogen-Induced Anti-Respiratory Substances and Their Effects &#34;One of the anti-respiratory substances produced by estrogen is carbon monoxide (Tschugguel, et al., 2001). Another inhibitor of mitochondrial oxidation, hydrogen sulfide, is also increased by estrogen (Lechuga, et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nad plus</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Hypothyroidism and the Risk of Reductive Stress &#34;The weak oxidative metabolism in hypothyroidism makes it easy to enter a state of reductive stress, with a shift toward a higher concentration of NADH and lactate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on niacinamide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</guid>
      <description>Defense Mechanisms Against Nitric Oxide: The Nutritional Angle &#34;Some of the most important anti-nitric oxide defenses are progesterone, vitamin E, vitamin K, vitamin A, niacinamide, coffee, aspirin, and foods containing flavonoids, terpenoids, polyphenols, and sterols. Grass-fed milk contains a variety of polyphenols. Citrus fruits, many tropical fruits (e.g., guavas, longans, and lychees), and cooked mushrooms are good sources of apigenin, naringenin and related chemicals.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nitric oxide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</guid>
      <description>ApoE4 and Alzheimer&amp;#39;s Disease Risk &#34;people with an abnormal lipoprotein, apoE4, are more likely to develop Alzheimers disease, and that abnormal protein is known to cause increased production of NO (&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Questioning Neodarwinism Through Hormetic Toxin Analysis &#34;If toxins such as CO and NO are beneficial, hormetically, when they occur in city air, then obviously they must be very beneficial when they are produced in the body by enzymes, which evolved through the natural selection of things that supported survival—there is a clear Panglossian aspect to neodarwinism, everything exists because of its fitness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on oxidation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</guid>
      <description>Estrogen&amp;#39;s Influence on Cellular Metabolism and Differentiation &#34;1 interpreted estrogens role in reproduction and cell proliferation in terms of an idea that was discussed by Otto Warburg and others. In this view, multiplication is the basic, simplest function of any cell, and it is supported by inefficient non-oxidative metabolism, while the differentiation of cells to form part of a stable multicellular organism requires the highly efficient oxidativ&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on parathyroid hormone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</guid>
      <description>Complex Mechanisms in Pseudohypoxic State Perpetuation &#34;There are several important mechanisms that are involved in perpetuating a pseudohypoxic state, and they can operate in a single tissue or organ, as well as in a generalized way throughout the organism. The thing that is often overlooked is the coherent overlapping interaction of the structural sulfhydryl redox system (-SH, -SS-), the redox regulation of gene expression, the glycolytic and oxidative energy metabolisms, regulation of pH and ionic selectivity, osmolarity, and solvent properties, especially the hydroephobic/hydrophilic balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnenolone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Indirect Role in Hormonal Balance and Stress &#34;Pregnenolone doesnt have the direct hormonal effects, but its the precursor, and by stopping exaggerated stress reactions it is likely to help&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on progesterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Progesterone&amp;#39;s Potential Anticancer Properties Underexplored &#34;Progesterone has a wide spectrum of anticancer activity, but as far as I know only synthetic progestins have been used medically. Although I used myself it on things that appeared to be very active melanomas, I usually recommend a slightly hyperthyroid state for helping to control it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prolactin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protective inhibition</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</guid>
      <description>Nitric Oxide: Central Factor in Shock State Dynamics &#34;nitric oxide was a central factor in the shock state, and that inhibiting its formation could alleviate the shock state. The state of shock was often called circulatory failure, from excessive vasodilation, s0 it was easy to see a role for the vasodilator nitric oxide in circulatory collapse;&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Estrogen-Induced Anti-Respiratory Substances and Their Effects &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on PUFAs</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</guid>
      <description>Quick Recovery from Stress with Low PUFA &#34;a person relatively free of PUFA will be likely to recover very quickly from prolonged stress.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Inadequacy of Blood Tests for Thyroid Hormone Levels &#34;Measuring the amount of thyroid hormone in the blood isnt a good way to evaluate adequacy of thyroid function, since the response of tissues to the hormone can be suppressed (for example, by unsaturated fats).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on science</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</guid>
      <description>Inadequacy of Blood Tests for Thyroid Hormone Levels &#34;Measuring the amount of thyroid hormone in the blood isnt a good way to evaluate adequacy of thyroid function, since the response of tissues to the hormone can be suppressed (for example, by unsaturated fats).&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Thyroid Hormone as Fundamental Anti-Stress Factor &#34;In a sense, the thyroid hormone is the basic anti-stress hormone, since it is required for the production of the adrenal and pregnancy hormones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on selenium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on serotonin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</guid>
      <description>Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer. It also has calcium blocking action, aldosterone antagonism, and antagonizes serotonins antidiuretic effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;The imbalances of endorphins, serotonin, catecholamines, and other nerve-regulators that have been seen in autism sometimes can be produced in adults by combined fatigue and poor nutrition, and when the livers glycogen is depleted, it can be hard to restore the balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sugar</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Starch&amp;#39;s Nutritional Impact Compared to Sugar &#34;When starch is well cooked, and eaten with some fat and the essential nutrients, its safe, except that its more likely than sugar to produce fat, and isnt as effective for mineral balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on testosterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</guid>
      <description>The Foundational Role of Progesterone and DHEA &#34;Progesterone and DHEA are the precursors for the other more specialized steroid hormones, including cortisol, aldosterone (sodium-retaining hormone), estrogen, and testosterone.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Steroids&amp;#39; Reversal of Aging Skin and Hair Growth Restoration &#34;People who studied the effects of steroids on aging skin found that the steroids which reversed structural age changes in the skin (progesterone, testosterone, pregnenolone) sometimes restored hair growth&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the brain</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the heart</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</guid>
      <description>Balancing Calorie Intake with Physical Activity Levels &#34;often ate more than 5000 calories, but when Im completely sedentary for more than ten hours daily, my energy requirement is much lower. The calorie intake should be balanced to your heat production and activity.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Stress-Related Cortisone&amp;#39;s Role in Heart Attacks &#34;According to Meerson, heart attacks are provoked and aggravated by the cortisone produced during stress.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the immune system</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</guid>
      <description>Historical Perspectives on Autoimmune Disease Treatment &#34;The idea of autoimmune disease can be traced back to Paul Ehrlich’s theory of immunity, and his idea of a therapeutic magic bullet has dominated the medical approach to treating the autoimmune diseases.&#34;
- November 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Metchnikoff and Beyond: The Immune System&amp;#39;s Harmony with the Microbiome &#34;The embryologist Elie Metchnikoff looked at immunity as an aspect of the organism’s maintenance of its own integrity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the liver</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on thyroid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</guid>
      <description>Contextualizing the Unphysiological Dosing of T3 Hormone &#34;Since the body normally produces about 4 mcg of T3 in an hour, taking 10 or 20 mcg at once is unphysiological.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Thyroid as Primary Regulator of Respiratory Adaptation &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on zinc</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
