<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ray Peat Explained</title>
    <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ray Peat Explained</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 08:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raypeatexplained.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on acetazolamide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-acetazolamide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-acetazolamide/</guid>
      <description>Acetazolamide&amp;#39;s Respiratory Impact &#34;acetazolamide, stimulates respiration by changing CO2 and pH;&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Therapeutic Potentials of Carbon Dioxide Usage &#34;Direct use of carbon dioxide is likely to be helpful in all the situations that are known to be benefitted by acetazolamide, without the risk of allergy to that drug—traumatic brain edema, mountain sickness, osteoporosis, epilepsy, glaucoma, hyperactivity (ADHD), inflammation, polyps of the intestine, and arthritis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on adaptation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-adaptation/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid as Primary Regulator of Respiratory Adaptation &#34;Thyroid is the main regulatory and adaptive substance for respiration.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Harmful Effects of Prolonged Cortisone During Stress &#34;Meersons work has revealed in a detailed way how the usually beneficial hormone of adaptation, cortisone, can cause so many other harmful effects when its action is too prolonged or too intense.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aging</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aging/</guid>
      <description>Steroids&amp;#39; Reversal of Aging Skin and Hair Growth Restoration &#34;People who studied the effects of steroids on aging skin found that the steroids which reversed structural age changes in the skin (progesterone, testosterone, pregnenolone) sometimes restored hair growth&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Oxygen, Iron, and Their Roles in Aging and Tissue Degradation &#34;I think oxygen wastage is a central event in aging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ammonia</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ammonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ammonia/</guid>
      <description>Lithium&amp;#39;s Treatment for Mood Disorders &#34;Lithium has been used for many years to treat various mood disorders, including anxiety and depression, and it reduces activation of the NMDA system, possibly by binding ammonia.&#34;
- January 2017 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Hypothyroidism&amp;#39;s Link to Chronic Stress and Metabolic Issues &#34;In hypothyroidism, with lowered oxidative metabolism, the organism is never far from stress and hyperventilation, with the chronic production of lactate and ammonia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on antioxidants</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-antioxidants/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-antioxidants/</guid>
      <description>Alcohol&amp;#39;s Antioxidant Benefits &#34;Small amounts of alcohol can have some good antioxidant effects,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Vitamins&amp;#39; Role in Protecting Against Iron-Induced Toxicity &#34;Vitamin C in excess can contribute to the toxicity of iron, but in the right amount, vitamin C is metabolically linked with vitamin E in protecting against the toxic free radicals produced by iron. Vitamin A also functions as an anti-oxidant, when the amount of oxygen present is very low--which is when iron toxicity is at its worst.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on aspirin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-aspirin/</guid>
      <description>Aspirin&amp;#39;s Increased Vitamin K Requirement &#34;aspirin makes you need more vitamin K, even when you arent using much. People who use aspirin for arthritis or cancer often take several grams a day.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Germicidal Properties of Aspirin &#34;Aspirin has a mild germicidal effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Reducing Aspirin&amp;#39;s Stomach Reactions &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ATP</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-atp/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid&amp;#39;s Impact on Caloric Needs and Glucose Regulation &#34;In my teens and twenties, I needed about 8000 calories per day when I was physically active, about 4000 to 5000 when I was sedentary, but after I took thyroid, I needed only about half as many calories. Thyroid is the basic regulator of blood glucose, and it causes it to be fully oxidized for energy, so that it produces ATP efficiently, on relatively few calories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on biological energy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-biological-energy/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Balancing Calorie Intake with Physical Activity Levels &#34;often ate more than 5000 calories, but when Im completely sedentary for more than ten hours daily, my energy requirement is much lower.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on calcium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-calcium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-calcium/</guid>
      <description>Effects of Long-Term Low Vitamin D on Parathyroid Glands &#34;If your vitamin D was very low for a long time, I think your parathyroid glands probably enlarged, and might take some time to normalize under the influence of a generous amount of vitamin D and calcium.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cancer</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cancer/</guid>
      <description>Aspirin&amp;#39;s Increased Vitamin K Requirement &#34;aspirin makes you need more vitamin K, even when you arent using much. People who use aspirin for arthritis or cancer often take several grams a day.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Endorphins&amp;#39; Possible Role in Ovarian Cancer Symptoms &#34;I think excess endorphins are often the problem, and the antagonist can sometimes be helpful. The endorphins differ in their effects on the two sides of the body, so when I knew two women (within the same year) who had been having mysterious one-sided symptoms for a few months before discovering that they had ovarian cancer (on the same side), I thought that the endorphins were probably involved, maybe to suppress pain on that side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cholesterol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cholesterol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cholesterol/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Animal Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Conversion into Steroids, Role of Thyroid &#34;In animals, cholesterol is the basic sterol molecule, which is massively converted into other substances, including the steroid hormones. Thyroid hormone and vitamin A are required for this conversion.&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on ciproheptadine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-ciproheptadine/</guid>
      <description>Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer. It also has calcium blocking action, aldosterone antagonism, and antagonizes serotonins antidiuretic effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Mitigating Excessive Serotonin&amp;#39;s Harmful Effects &#34;Avoiding prolonged fasting and stressful exercise that increase free fatty acids, and combining sugars with proteins to keep free fatty acids low, and using aspirin, niacinamide, or cyproheptadine to reduce the formation of free fatty acids by unavoidable stress, avoiding an excess of phosphate relative to calcium in the diet, having milk and other antistress foods at bedtime or during the night, and being in a brightly lighted environment during the day, with regular sunlight exposure, can minimize the harmful effects of excessive serotonin and reduce the inflammation, fibrosis, and atrophy associated with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on CO2</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-co2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-co2/</guid>
      <description>Acetazolamide&amp;#39;s Respiratory Impact &#34;acetazolamide, stimulates respiration by changing CO2 and pH;&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Estrogen-Induced Anti-Respiratory Substances and Their Effects &#34;One of the anti-respiratory substances produced by estrogen is carbon monoxide (Tschugguel, et al., 2001). Another inhibitor of mitochondrial oxidation, hydrogen sulfide, is also increased by estrogen (Lechuga, et al., 2015).&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Unraveling the Complexities of Fat and Carbohydrate Metabolism &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on copper</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-copper/</guid>
      <description> Copper Solution&amp;#39;s Immediate Effects on Hair Pigmentation &#34;I found that applying a weak solution of copper just once would restore color immediately to eyebrows, or to about 10% of sideburn hairs,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on cortisol</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-cortisol/</guid>
      <description>Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;Pregnenolone isnt a hormone, but it normalizes the steroid hormones, preventing excess cortisol and helping to normalize aldosterone, so it should be helpful for any stress including surgery. P&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Progesterone&amp;#39;s Non-Suppressive Effect on Its Synthesis &#34;The fact that progesterone (and probably pregnenolone) stimulates its own synthesis means that taking it does not suppress the bodys ability to synthesize it, as happens with cortisol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on depression</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-depression/</guid>
      <description>Blood Glucose&amp;#39;s Role in Cortisone Formation &#34;the basic signal which causes cortisone to be formed is a drop in the blood glucose level. The increased energy requirement of any stress tends to cause the blood sugar to fall slightly, but hypothyroidism itself tends to depress blood sugar.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Lithium&amp;#39;s Treatment for Mood Disorders &#34;Lithium has been used for many years to treat various mood disorders, including anxiety and depression, and it reduces activation of the NMDA system, possibly by binding ammonia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on development</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-development/</guid>
      <description>Progesterone&amp;#39;s Positive Effect on Brain Growth &#34;Marion Diamond, who studied the effects of stimulation on rats brain development, found that pregnancy or progesterone treatment--like freedom and stimulation--caused the brain to grow, and estrogen--like stress--caused it to shrink.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Adaptation Strategies of Plants and Animals to Energy Scarcity &#34;oth plants and animals are able to adapt-phylogenetically and ontogenetically, i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dhea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dhea/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote The Foundational Role of Progesterone and DHEA &#34;Progesterone and DHEA are the precursors for the other more specialized steroid hormones, including cortisol, aldosterone (sodium-retaining hormone), estrogen, and testosterone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on digestion</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-digestion/</guid>
      <description>Intestinal Irritation Link to Tinnitus Through Endotoxin &#34;anything that irritates the intestine can cause tinnitus by increasing endotoxin absorption.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Julien de la Mettrie&amp;#39;s Physiology Based on Organ Function &#34;Thinking of several kinds of biological facts, including the intrinsic motility or irritability of the intestine and heart, and the regeneration of the hydra from small fragments, Julien de la Mettrie proposed a new kind of physiology, based on the idea of organization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on dopamine</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-dopamine/</guid>
      <description>Exploring Sensory Experience Modification in Parkinson&amp;#39;s Therapy &#34;Without knowing the basic causes of Parkinson’s disease (and it isn’t very helpful to keep hearing that it’s caused by the death of dopaminergic cells in the substantial nigra), we don’t know how much can be achieved by way of modifying sensory experience, but if we consider the powerful biological effects of learned helpless, and the simplicity with which it can be alleviated, we can imagine that the therapeutic possibilities in that direction might be great.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-epilepsy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-epilepsy/</guid>
      <description>Obstacles in Understanding Key Biological Concepts &#34;Some of the best known ideas of biology—including genes, membranes and receptors—have blocked, and continue to block, understanding of aging, cancer, stress, shock, epilepsy, regeneration, perception, and thinking.&#34;
- January 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Therapeutic Potentials of Carbon Dioxide Usage &#34;Direct use of carbon dioxide is likely to be helpful in all the situations that are known to be benefitted by acetazolamide, without the risk of allergy to that drug—traumatic brain edema, mountain sickness, osteoporosis, epilepsy, glaucoma, hyperactivity (ADHD), inflammation, polyps of the intestine, and arthritis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on estrogen</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-estrogen/</guid>
      <description>Endorphins&amp;#39; Possible Role in Ovarian Cancer Symptoms &#34;I think excess endorphins are often the problem, and the antagonist can sometimes be helpful. The endorphins differ in their effects on the two sides of the body, so when I knew two women (within the same year) who had been having mysterious one-sided symptoms for a few months before discovering that they had ovarian cancer (on the same side), I thought that the endorphins were probably involved, maybe to suppress pain on that side.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on free fatty acids</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-free-fatty-acids/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-free-fatty-acids/</guid>
      <description>The Metabolic Aftermath of Nitric Oxide Exposure &#34;a diabetes-like state is created by nitric oxide damage, forcing the use of fatty acids instead of glucose for fuel.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote The Consequences of Impaired Glucose Oxidation and Shift to Fatty Acids &#34;When the oxidation of glucose is impaired, with fatty acids being oxidized for energy, there is usually a decrease in the overall metabolic rate, as well as a shift toward a more reductive biochemistry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on gaba</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gaba/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Gilbert Ling</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-gilbert-ling/</guid>
      <description>Diet&amp;#39;s Impact on Cancer Incidence and Metabolic Rate &#34;In 1927, German researchers reported that a fat-free diet prevented the occurrence of spontaneous cancers in rats. Since, a little later, other workers found that the elimination of unsaturated fats from the diet not only prevented cancer, but also caused a large increase in the metabolic rate, it might have been possible to conclude that it is not living which kills us, but something in the environment&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on Hans Selye</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-hans-selye/</guid>
      <description> Intestinal Stress Effects Overlooked &#34;While the effects of stress on the intestine have been recognized since Hans Selye described the general adaptation syndrome (with intestinal bleeding as an early sign of stress), that hasnt been taken into account in any of the large brain trauma or stroke studies.&#34;
- March 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on inflammation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-inflammation/</guid>
      <description>Hypothyroidism&amp;#39;s Impact on Cortisone and Inflammation &#34;While hypothyroidism makes the body require more cortisone to sustain blood sugar and energy production, it also limits the ability to produce cortisone, so in some cases stress produces symptoms resulting from a deficiency of cortisone, including various forms of arthritis and more generalized types of chronic inflammation.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Rethinking Nitric Oxide&amp;#39;s Role in Cellular Stress &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on intelligence</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-intelligence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-intelligence/</guid>
      <description>The Development of Intelligence Through Interaction and Learning &#34;Our intelligence develops as we grow into the world, such as it is, and our world includes things that we learn about, and the people that we learn from&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Larger Brain Correlates with Intelligence, Longevity &#34;In animals generally, a larger brain is associated not only with higher intelligence, but with greater longevity&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on lactic acid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-lactic-acid/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Revisiting the Warburg Effect: Glycolysis and Cancer Metabolism &#34;t an extreme, the reductive energy derived from aerobic glycolysis can be consumed by the synthesis of fat, permitting glycolysis to proceed, and this can lead to cancer cells that oxidize fatty acids for energy, while converting glucose to fats and lactic acid.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on learned helplessness</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-learned-helplessness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-learned-helplessness/</guid>
      <description>Metabolic Shifts Under Extreme Stress and Learned Helplessness &#34;When the organism as a whole is overburdened, with stress physiology passing into the learned helplessness™ or shock states, its metabolism shifts in the direction of reductive, pseudohypoxic metabolism, in which the nervous system suppresses oxidative metabolism,&#34;
- July 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Exploring Sensory Experience Modification in Parkinson&amp;#39;s Therapy &#34;Without knowing the basic causes of Parkinson’s disease (and it isn’t very helpful to keep hearing that it’s caused by the death of dopaminergic cells in the substantial nigra), we don’t know how much can be achieved by way of modifying sensory experience, but if we consider the powerful biological effects of learned helpless, and the simplicity with which it can be alleviated, we can imagine that the therapeutic possibilities in that direction might be great.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on magnesium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-magnesium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-magnesium/</guid>
      <description>Stress-Related Cortisone&amp;#39;s Role in Heart Attacks &#34;According to Meerson, heart attacks are provoked and aggravated by the cortisone produced during stress. (Meerson and his colleagues have demonstrated that the progress of a heart attack can be halted by a treatment including natural substances such as vitamin E and magnesium.)&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Overlooked Nutritional Factors in Infertility &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on menopause</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-menopause/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-menopause/</guid>
      <description>Cortisol Levels and Inflammation Post-Menopause &#34;Starting suddenly around the time of menopause, cortisol is higher, probably as compensation for the lost stabilizing effects of progesterone, and the increased inflammatory processes resulting from lower body temperature.&#34;
- November 2020 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Aromatase Activity and Hormonal Impact at Menopause &#34;Aromatase, the enzyme that produces estrogen, is present in muscles, fat, blood vessels, and many other tissues, and its activity is increased by cortisol, and decreased by progesterone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on metabolism</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-metabolism/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Steroid Hormones&amp;#39; Integral Role in Animal Physiology &#34;The steroid hormones are involved in all aspects of animal physiology, and overlap with control functions of the nervous system, peptide hormones, metabolites, prostaglandins, cyclic nucleotides, etc&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on microparticles</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-microparticles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-microparticles/</guid>
      <description>Hoyle&amp;#39;s Cosmological Research Suggests Cosmic Dust&amp;#39;s Biological Nature &#34;Fred Hoyle and his colleagues have done some work which parallels that of Vernadsky, and which encourages a livelier way of thinking about cosmology. They have gathered spectroscopic evidence that cosmic dust (which makes up a significant part of the mass in the universe) more closely resembles bacteria than the other materials or particles which have been suggested (E. coli were used for spectroscopic comparison).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on mitochondria</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-mitochondria/</guid>
      <description>Diet and Stress Resistance in Age-Related Oxidative Changes &#34;The avoidance of oxidatively toxic heavy metals, and the maintenance of respiration, with an absence of the highly peroxidizable unsaturated fats in the diet (and a lower level of them in the storage tissues) would probably make the animals tolerate stress better (EFA deficient mitochondria are more resistant to oxidative injury, and vitamin E prevents many stress-associated problems), and might inhibit the age-related oxidative changes in serum albumin, red blood cells, and other tissues&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nad plus</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nad-plus/</guid>
      <description>Identifying Reductive Stress Through Metabolic Ratios &#34;With aging, and during stress, animals metabolism shifts toward reduction, with a higher ratio of lactate to pyruvate, of NADH to NAD, of ascorbate to dehydroascorbate, etc., a state of reductive stress.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Hypothyroidism and the Risk of Reductive Stress &#34;The weak oxidative metabolism in hypothyroidism makes it easy to enter a state of reductive stress, with a shift toward a higher concentration of NADH and lactate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on niacinamide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-niacinamide/</guid>
      <description>Defense Mechanisms Against Nitric Oxide: The Nutritional Angle &#34;Some of the most important anti-nitric oxide defenses are progesterone, vitamin E, vitamin K, vitamin A, niacinamide, coffee, aspirin, and foods containing flavonoids, terpenoids, polyphenols, and sterols. Grass-fed milk contains a variety of polyphenols. Citrus fruits, many tropical fruits (e.g., guavas, longans, and lychees), and cooked mushrooms are good sources of apigenin, naringenin and related chemicals.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on nitric oxide</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-nitric-oxide/</guid>
      <description>Rethinking Nitric Oxide&amp;#39;s Role in Cellular Stress &#34;If we called nitric oxide an anti-respiratory pro-inflammatory substance produced mostly by stressed cells, we would be very cautious about medical techniques to increase its production.&#34;
- January 2016 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nitric Oxide: Central Factor in Shock State Dynamics &#34;nitric oxide was a central factor in the shock state, and that inhibiting its formation could alleviate the shock state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on oxidation</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-oxidation/</guid>
      <description>Analyzing the Paradoxical Features of Older Blood &#34;Two clear differences have been found between old blood and young blood. The albumin in old blood is in a more oxidized state. (I think it was the famous gerontologist, Verzar, who first reported this.) Although, at least in aging humans, there is much less oxygen in the blood, something causes the albumin to be in a more oxidized state in older blood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on parathyroid hormone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-parathyroid-hormone/</guid>
      <description>Animal Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Conversion into Steroids, Role of Thyroid &#34;In animals, cholesterol is the basic sterol molecule, which is massively converted into other substances, including the steroid hormones. Thyroid hormone and vitamin A are required for this conversion.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Inadequacy of Blood Tests for Thyroid Hormone Levels &#34;Measuring the amount of thyroid hormone in the blood isnt a good way to evaluate adequacy of thyroid function, since the response of tissues to the hormone can be suppressed (for example, by unsaturated fats).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pre-eclampsia</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pre-eclampsia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pre-eclampsia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnancy</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnancy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnancy/</guid>
      <description>1930&amp;#39;s Understanding of Hormones in Organism Resistance &#34;By the 1930s, it was well established that the resistance of the organism depended on the energy produced by respiration under the influence of the thyroid gland, as well as on the adrenal hormones, and that the hormones of pregnancy (especially progesterone) could substitute for the adrenal hormones&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Thyroid Hormone as Fundamental Anti-Stress Factor &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on pregnenolone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pregnenolone/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Indirect Role in Hormonal Balance and Stress &#34;Pregnenolone doesnt have the direct hormonal effects, but its the precursor, and by stopping exaggerated stress reactions it is likely to help&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Pregnenolone&amp;#39;s Influence on Steroid Hormones and Stress Mitigation &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on progesterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-progesterone/</guid>
      <description>Personal Experience: Progesterone and DHEA Affect on Melanomas &#34;I had some probable melanomas years ago, and I found that progesterone and DHEA and increased thyroid caused them to disappear quickly.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Progesterone&amp;#39;s Potential Anticancer Properties Underexplored &#34;Progesterone has a wide spectrum of anticancer activity, but as far as I know only synthetic progestins have been used medically. Although I used myself it on things that appeared to be very active melanomas, I usually recommend a slightly hyperthyroid state for helping to control it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on prolactin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-prolactin/</guid>
      <description>Denckla&amp;#39;s Theory of a Pituitary Death Hormone in Aging &#34;W. Donner Denckla suggested that there is a death hormone in the pituitary gland, which appears at puberty and initiates the process of aging by suppressing the use of oxygen. He maintained that merely providing thyroid supplement wouldnt protect against it, and that it was a distinct hormone, although it tended to appear in tissue extracts in association with prolactin and growth hormone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protective inhibition</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protective-inhibition/</guid>
      <description>Diet and Stress Resistance in Age-Related Oxidative Changes &#34;The avoidance of oxidatively toxic heavy metals, and the maintenance of respiration, with an absence of the highly peroxidizable unsaturated fats in the diet (and a lower level of them in the storage tissues) would probably make the animals tolerate stress better (EFA deficient mitochondria are more resistant to oxidative injury, and vitamin E prevents many stress-associated problems), and might inhibit the age-related oxidative changes in serum albumin, red blood cells, and other tissues&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on protein</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protein/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-protein/</guid>
      <description>Superiority of Animal-Based Protein Sources &#34;Milk, cheese, and eggs are better proteins, anyway, because of the better calcium/phosphate ratio.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on PUFAs</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-pufas/</guid>
      <description>Quick Recovery from Stress with Low PUFA &#34;a person relatively free of PUFA will be likely to recover very quickly from prolonged stress.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Inadequacy of Blood Tests for Thyroid Hormone Levels &#34;Measuring the amount of thyroid hormone in the blood isnt a good way to evaluate adequacy of thyroid function, since the response of tissues to the hormone can be suppressed (for example, by unsaturated fats).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on salt and sodium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-salt-and-sodium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-salt-and-sodium/</guid>
      <description>Overlooked Nutritional Factors in Infertility &#34;Too much carotene, too little vitamin A, not enough magnesium or sodium, and too much cortisol are commonly overlooked factors in infertility.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Diet&amp;#39;s Role in Preventing Pregnancy Complications &#34;Adequate protein, glucose, and sodium to maintain blood volume will prevent most of these problems of later pregnancy, unless the hormonal imbalance is very bad&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on science</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-science/</guid>
      <description>Inadequacy of Blood Tests for Thyroid Hormone Levels &#34;Measuring the amount of thyroid hormone in the blood isnt a good way to evaluate adequacy of thyroid function, since the response of tissues to the hormone can be suppressed (for example, by unsaturated fats).&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Thyroid Hormone as Fundamental Anti-Stress Factor &#34;In a sense, the thyroid hormone is the basic anti-stress hormone, since it is required for the production of the adrenal and pregnancy hormones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on selenium</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-selenium/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on serotonin</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-serotonin/</guid>
      <description>Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer. It also has calcium blocking action, aldosterone antagonism, and antagonizes serotonins antidiuretic effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;The imbalances of endorphins, serotonin, catecholamines, and other nerve-regulators that have been seen in autism sometimes can be produced in adults by combined fatigue and poor nutrition, and when the livers glycogen is depleted, it can be hard to restore the balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sleep</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sleep/</guid>
      <description>Cyproheptadine&amp;#39;s Multifaceted Benefits for Sleep and Cancer &#34;Cyproheptadine, 2 to 4 mg at bedtime, would help with his sleep as well as the cancer. It also has calcium blocking action, aldosterone antagonism, and antagonizes serotonins antidiuretic effect.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote REM Sleep and Orienting Reflex Enhance Thinking Flexibility &#34;REM sleep and the orienting reflex both promote flexibility and fluidity of thinking, with increased sensitivity to motion,&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on sugar</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-sugar/</guid>
      <description>Positive Dietary Changes Normalize Energy Burst Fluctuations &#34;If the rest of your diet is good, the energy bursts from sugar should level off, and become a steady increased metabolic rate.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Starch&amp;#39;s Nutritional Impact Compared to Sugar &#34;When starch is well cooked, and eaten with some fat and the essential nutrients, its safe, except that its more likely than sugar to produce fat, and isnt as effective for mineral balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on testosterone</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-testosterone/</guid>
      <description>The Foundational Role of Progesterone and DHEA &#34;Progesterone and DHEA are the precursors for the other more specialized steroid hormones, including cortisol, aldosterone (sodium-retaining hormone), estrogen, and testosterone.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Steroids&amp;#39; Reversal of Aging Skin and Hair Growth Restoration &#34;People who studied the effects of steroids on aging skin found that the steroids which reversed structural age changes in the skin (progesterone, testosterone, pregnenolone) sometimes restored hair growth&#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the brain</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-brain/</guid>
      <description>Thyroid as Primary Regulator of Respiratory Adaptation &#34;Thyroid is the main regulatory and adaptive substance for respiration.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the heart</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-heart/</guid>
      <description>Stress-Related Cortisone&amp;#39;s Role in Heart Attacks &#34;According to Meerson, heart attacks are provoked and aggravated by the cortisone produced during stress. (Meerson and his colleagues have demonstrated that the progress of a heart attack can be halted by a treatment including natural substances such as vitamin E and magnesium.)&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote The Interplay of Energy Flow and Structural Development &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the immune system</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-immune-system/</guid>
      <description>Immunity: Innate vs. Adaptive in Organisms &#34;In the 1960s, when antibodies were being studied intensively, Metchnikoff’s approach was called innate immunity, something more primitive and undifferentiated than the evolutionarily more advanced adaptive immunity of the B and T cells, bone and thymus cells. At that time, however, an example of something like adaptive immunity, a learned response to a toxin, had already been demonstrated to exist in plants,&#34;
- January 2020 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Inflammation&amp;#39;s Role in Universal Pathology &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on the liver</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-the-liver/</guid>
      <description>Brain&amp;#39;s High Energy Demands and Nutritional Needs &#34;the brain is energetically a very expensive organ in terms of its energy requirements, and the liver has to be very efficient to meet its needs, so when there is a nutritional or hormonal problem, the problems can be especially intense. Nutritional needs for sugar, protein, vitamins, and minerals can be very high.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Nutritional Deficits&amp;#39; Impact on Neurological Imbalances &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on thyroid</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-thyroid/</guid>
      <description>Contextualizing the Unphysiological Dosing of T3 Hormone &#34;Since the body normally produces about 4 mcg of T3 in an hour, taking 10 or 20 mcg at once is unphysiological.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Thyroid Hormone&amp;#39;s Role in Cholesterol Conversion &#34;Thyroid tends to lower cholesterol by converting it into pregnenolone and other steroids,&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Thyroid as Primary Regulator of Respiratory Adaptation &#34;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on urea</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-urea/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-urea/</guid>
      <description>Sperm Cell Replacement with Simple Substances &#34;Loeb demonstrated that the specific biological stimulus of a sperm cell, interacting with a receptor in the egg, wasn’t needed to fertilize an egg; sea water, with added salt or sugar or urea, or acid or alkali, was enough&#34;
- January 2019 - Ray Peat&amp;#39;s Newsletter Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Urea&amp;#39;s Lost Role in Brain Treatment &#34;50 years ago, urea was widely used to treat brain injuries, but a misunderstanding of its physical properties, and now the availability of the highly profitable vaptans, have displaced it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin A</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-a/</guid>
      <description>Animal Cholesterol&amp;#39;s Conversion into Steroids, Role of Thyroid &#34;In animals, cholesterol is the basic sterol molecule, which is massively converted into other substances, including the steroid hormones. Thyroid hormone and vitamin A are required for this conversion.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Vitamins&amp;#39; Role in Protecting Against Iron-Induced Toxicity &#34;Vitamin C in excess can contribute to the toxicity of iron, but in the right amount, vitamin C is metabolically linked with vitamin E in protecting against the toxic free radicals produced by iron.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin D</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-d/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-d/</guid>
      <description>Effects of Long-Term Low Vitamin D on Parathyroid Glands &#34;If your vitamin D was very low for a long time, I think your parathyroid glands probably enlarged, and might take some time to normalize under the influence of a generous amount of vitamin D and calcium.&#34;
- Email Response by Ray Peat
Upvote 0 upvotes Copy Link to Quote Common Inhibitors of Carbonic Anhydrase Enzyme &#34;Among the common inhibitors of carbonic anhydrase are the mildly oxidizing flavonoids such as apigenin and fisetin, some polyphenols, vitamin B1, vitamin D (Mras, et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin E</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-e/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-e/</guid>
      <description>Vitamins&amp;#39; Role in Protecting Against Iron-Induced Toxicity &#34;Vitamin C in excess can contribute to the toxicity of iron, but in the right amount, vitamin C is metabolically linked with vitamin E in protecting against the toxic free radicals produced by iron. Vitamin A also functions as an anti-oxidant, when the amount of oxygen present is very low--which is when iron toxicity is at its worst.&#34;
- Generative Energy Restoring The Wholeness Of Life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on vitamin K</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-k/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-vitamin-k/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Peat on zinc</title>
      <link>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2023 15:15:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://raypeatexplained.com/ray-peat-on-zinc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
